<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English vsurer; or Vsury condemned, by the most learned and famous diuines of the Church of England and dedicated to all his Maiesties subiects, for the stay of further increase of the same. Collected by Iohn Blaxton, preacher of Gods VVord at Osmington, in Dorcet-shire.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73521</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3129.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124641</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900320</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900320</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150798</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73521)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150798)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1982:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English vsurer; or Vsury condemned, by the most learned and famous diuines of the Church of England and dedicated to all his Maiesties subiects, for the stay of further increase of the same. Collected by Iohn Blaxton, preacher of Gods VVord at Osmington, in Dorcet-shire.</title>
                  <author>Blaxton, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 84 p. : bill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Iohn Norton, and are to bee sold by Iohn Long, in Dorchester,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>One of three imprint variants of this edition.</note>
                  <note>E1r catchword: 'weather'; a variant has quire E in different setting with E1r catchword: 'or'--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ a⁴ B-L⁴ M² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Usury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ENGLISH VSVRER; <hi>OR</hi> VSVRY CONDEMNED, <hi>BY</hi> The moſt learned and famous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to all his Maieſties Subiects, for the ſtay of further increaſe of the ſame. Collected By IOHN BLAXTON, Preacher of Gods Word at <hi>Oſmington,</hi> in <hi>Dorcet-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Caluin,</hi> Epiſt. de Vſura.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adeò plus quàm rarum est eundem eſſe hominem probum et faeneratorem.</hi> It is more then rare, (or it is very ſeldome ſeene,) that one and the ſame perſon, ſhould be both an honeſt man, and an vſurer.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by IOHN NORTON, and are to bee ſold by IOHN LONG, in <hi>Dorchester.</hi> 1634.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="emblem">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:4"/>
            <lg>
               <head>The Illuſtration.</head>
               <l>THe <hi>Couetous wretch,</hi> to what may we compare,</l>
               <l>better then <hi>Swine:</hi> both of one nature are,</l>
               <l>One <hi>grumbles,</hi> th' other <hi>grunts:</hi> both groſſe and dull,</l>
               <l>hungry, <hi>ſtill feeding,</hi> and yet neuer <hi>full.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reſemblance from their <hi>habits</hi> may be had</l>
               <l>the one in <hi>Furre,</hi> th' other in <hi>Briſtles</hi> clad.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rich men</hi> by others ſweat augment their pounds:</l>
               <l>the <hi>Hog's</hi> ſtill rooting in the neighbours grounds.</l>
               <l>They neyther of them vpward caſt an eye,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>both</hi> downeward looke, and pray on what they ſpie,</l>
               <l>Nor differ they in <hi>death,</hi> The <hi>Brawne</hi> nought yeilds</l>
               <l>till cut tn <hi>Collers,</hi> into <hi>Cheekes</hi> and <hi>Shields,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like <hi>him</hi> the <hi>Vſurer</hi> howſoeuer fed,</l>
               <l>Profits none <hi>liuing,</hi> till himſelfe be <hi>dead.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Both with the <hi>Chriſtmas-boxe</hi> may well comply</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It</hi> not hing yeilds till broke, <hi>They</hi> till they dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man or userer seated at a table on which is laid the paraphernalia of his trade: coins, measures, books, etc.; beneath his seat is a strongbox; on the back of his chair, at his shoulder, is a black demon or devil</figDesc>
                  <head>The Engliſh Vſurer.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I ſay I will haue all</l>
                     <l>both Vſe &amp; principall.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of two pigs, one standing with its snout in the earth, the other lying on its back</figDesc>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Mine is the <hi>Vſurers</hi> deſire.</l>
                     <l>To roote in earth, wallow in Mire.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Liuing ſpare me,</l>
                     <l>and Dead ſhare me.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Caluin Epiſt. de Vſura.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>In repub. benè conſtitutâ nemo foenerator tolerabilis eſt, ſed omninò debet è conſortio hominum reijci:</hi> An Vſurer is not tolerable in a well eſtabliſhed Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, but vtterly to be reiected out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are ſome commit vſury,<note place="margin">Why ſome are vſurers.</note> not knowing it to be ſinne: eyther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue not the Word, or they vſe not the Word for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning of their hearts.<note place="margin">See M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Moſſe,</hi> Treatiſe of vſury Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Reader.</note> Thoſe that bee ignorant for want of the Word, are much to be pitied; and yet is their want that way, the iuſt puniſhment of ſinne. Thoſe that are ignorant for not vſing the Word, are ſharpely to be reproued, as thoſe whoſe ignorance accrewing from their owne negligence, is meere ſinne vnto them.<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Sextum Rom. preſby Ep. <hi>105.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>In vtriſque non eſt iuſta excuſatio, ſed iuſta condemnatio,</hi> ſayth <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Neyther of both can iuſtly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed; nay eyther of both is iuſtly to be condemned. Others commit vſury, and ſtand to excuſe it, alead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for themſelues the authority of men: to theſe I anſwer, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> did to the Gentiles, who grounded their religion vpon the authority of their Anceſtours, <hi>Id ſolum rectum eſt, quod ratio praeſcribit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lact. de Origine er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> not that which men ſay, but that which reaſon war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranteth, is right and to be approued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:6"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 23.2.</note>To them that alleadge <hi>examples,</hi> I anſwer with the ancient prouerbe, <hi>Viuitur preceptis non exemplis:</hi> we muſt liue by precepts, and not by examples. And with that of <hi>Moſes, Thou ſhalt not follow a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to doe euill.</hi> To them which iuſtifie vſury to be lawfull, I ſtand not heere to make anſwer: for to that end ſerueth the treatiſe following. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Cyprian. De Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorum.</note> I applie vnto them, that which <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſpake of ſome Teachers of his time, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulantes in tenebris, habere ſe lucem exiſtimant:</hi> walking in darkeneſſe, they ſuppoſe they haue the light.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diſtruſt in Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence the Vſurers ſin.</note>To them that pretend, they cannot otherwiſe liue, I replie: that they may accuſe themſelues of ſloth and idleneſſe, of infidelity and diſtruſt in Gods Prouidence: which is indeed the Vſurers ſinne.</p>
            <p>Others yet there are, who knowing the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to bee euill, and themſelues not being able to excuſe it, they turne their noſe vpon the very winde,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> like the weather Cocke, and like mad men rage at thoſe that would binde them for their benefit: and are like the Swine of which Chriſt ſpeaketh in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.6.</note> who when they haue Pearles throwne before them, turne againe, and all to rent thoſe that caſt them. God bee mercifull vnto theſe kind of Vſurers, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> (if it bee his will,) for their caſe is deſperate. They are like vnto a fooliſh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, who is ready to flie into the face of the Chirurgian, when hee ſearcheth his wound vnto
<pb facs="tcp:150798:6"/> the bottome, for the curing of it. What will follow hereupon? But the ruine of the Vſurer?</p>
            <p>Others, when the Miniſter preacheth againſt Vſury, encourage themſelues in their vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table courſe of life, by this conceit: that it is but his priuate opinion. This treatiſe will make it euident, that, <hi>Vſury to bee vnlawfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The moſt iudicious Diuines condemne Vſury.</note> proceeds not out of the mouths of ſome few <hi>Humoriſts</hi> in the Country, (for ſo the Vſurers account them:) but it is the iudgement of thoſe who ſit at the Helme, and deſeruedly are accounted pillars in the Church of God.</p>
            <p>As for the Author of this Treatiſe: vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that hee neyther lendeth, nor taketh vpon Vſury: for hee followes his calling,<note place="margin">Vſurers vile perſons Pſ. 15.</note> and doth not buſy himſelfe much with the affayers of the world. As for profeſt Vſurers, hee eſteemes them as vile perſons, in whoſe eyes they are moſt iuſtly contemned, but hee honoreth thoſe that feare the Lord. which the Vſurers do not. And therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free from the guiltineſſe of this ſinne, he may the moore freely giue ſentence vpon the vngodlineſſe thereof <hi>Iudicet ille de alterius errore</hi> (ſayth S. <hi>Ambroſe) qui non habet in ſeipſo quod condemnet: iudicet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, beati im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculati.</note> 
               <hi>qui non agit eadem quae in alio putauerit punienda.</hi> Let him iudge of another mans default, who hath not the ſame fault to condemne in himſelfe: let him iudge of another who committeth not the ſame thing which hee deemeth worthy the puniſhing in another.</p>
            <p>Know moreouer, that he is a thorough conformable
<pb facs="tcp:150798:7"/> Member and Miniſter of the Church of England. And for the Scope of this Treatiſe, it is for the information and ſaluation of thy ſoule, and his owne ſoule. Take the Treatiſe, and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Si quid ex vſu tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reperias, iuvame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus tuis apud deum; aliam mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedem non defidero. vale.</note> giue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy fellow member in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>John Blaxton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:7"/>
            <head>A Table of the Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. 1.</label>
               <item>VSury defined by Biſhop <hi>Downam,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fenton.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. 2.</label>
               <item>The diſtinction of vſury into mentall and actuall. Where actuall vſury is diſtinguiſhed from other contracts: as <hi>1</hi> From liberall contracts. <hi>2</hi> From all lawfull buying. <hi>3</hi> From lawfull Location or letting to hire. <hi>4</hi> From the contract of Partnerſhip. <hi>5</hi> From aduenturers vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>6</hi> From liberall vſury. <hi>7</hi> From recompencing vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which we call Intereſt.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 3.</label>
               <item>The teſtimony of ſixe learned Biſhops prouing it ſimply vnlawfull.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 4.</label>
               <item>The teſtimony of the learned Diuines of the Church of England condemning vſury.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 5.</label>
               <item>Cleare and apt Similies to which vſury and vſurers are reſembled.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 6.</label>
               <item>Anſwereth the obiections which are commonly made in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of vſury.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 7.</label>
               <item>That vſurers are bound to repent, and to make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:8"/>
            <head>The Names of the moſt Reuerend <hi>and learned Biſhops, and of the moſt learned and</hi> Iudiciall Diuines vſed in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <head>Biſhop</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> Sands <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Archbiſhop of</hi> Yorke.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Iewell <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> King <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Biſhop of</hi> London.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Babington <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Biſhop of</hi> Worceſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Downam, <hi>the hammer of vſurers, Lord Biſhop of</hi> Derry <hi>in</hi> Ireland.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Lake, <hi>late Lord Biſhop of</hi> Bath <hi>and</hi> Wels.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Doctor</head>
               <item>Pic.</item>
               <item>Willet.</item>
               <item>Sclater.</item>
               <item>Tayler.</item>
               <item>Smith.</item>
               <item>Preſton.</item>
               <item>Williams</item>
               <item>Web.</item>
               <item>Sutton.</item>
               <item>Wilſon.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Mr.</head>
               <item>Wilkinſon.</item>
               <item>Smith.</item>
               <item>Wheatly.</item>
               <item>Dod.</item>
               <item>Bolton.</item>
               <item>Perkins.</item>
               <item>Adams.</item>
               <item>Powel.</item>
               <item>Wilſon.</item>
               <item>Scudder.</item>
               <item>Rogers of</item>
               <item>Wethersfield</item>
               <item>Rogers of</item>
               <item>Meſſing</item>
               <item>Rogers of</item>
               <item>Dedham.</item>
               <item>Northbrooke</item>
               <item>Philips.</item>
               <item>Robrough.</item>
               <item>Moſſe.</item>
               <item>Fenton.</item>
               <item>Dyke.</item>
               <item>Bayne.</item>
               <item>Brinſley.</item>
               <item>Silueſter.</item>
               <item>Withers.</item>
               <item>Quarles.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:8"/>
            <head>The Charitable happy, the Vſurers accurſed.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>O!</hi> thrice, thrice happy he,<note place="margin">Bleſſed are the mercifull. Math. 5.7. Pſal. 37.19.</note> whoſe free deſires</l>
            <l>To charity a holy feruor fires:</l>
            <l>Who onely minds Gods glory, by his gift,</l>
            <l>And neyghbours good, without ſiniſter drift;</l>
            <l>Famine (familiar vnto rogues that range)</l>
            <l>Shall not come neere his garner, nor his grange:</l>
            <l>His fields, with Corne, abundant crop ſhall couer,</l>
            <l>His vines with Grapes, his hedge with Roſes ouer;</l>
            <l>His downes with ſheepe, his dayery grounds with Neat;</l>
            <l>His mounts with Kids, his moors with Oxen great;</l>
            <l>His groues with droues (increaſing night and day;)</l>
            <l>His hils with Heards, his ſmiling meads with Hay;</l>
            <l>His fens with foule, his pils, and pooles with Fiſh;</l>
            <l>His trees with fruits, with plenty euery diſh;</l>
            <l>Content and health (the beſt of earthly bliſſe)</l>
            <l>Shall euermore remaine with him and his;<note place="margin">Phil. 4.11.12. 1 Tim. 6.6.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Him, pride or enuy neuer ſhall molest;</l>
            <l>Or corſiue care, foe to repast and reſt.</l>
            <l>For, th' all-ſee eye still carefully reſpects</l>
            <l>The <hi>Almner's</hi> houſe, and euer it protects;<note place="margin">Eſay 58 8.9, 10, 11, &amp;c.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Till finally, when iuſtice endeth all,</l>
            <l>Sweet mercies voyce him to heau'ns Kingdome call.</l>
            <l>But th' Vſurer (how-euer here he thriue</l>
            <l>In heards and hoords) already dead aliue</l>
            <l>(No heat of loue, no heart to giue a mite,<note place="margin">Curſed are the vſures. Pſal. 15.5.</note>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:9"/>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.13.</note>Except to gaine and gather double by 't)</l>
            <l>Him, in that day (to him a day of woe)</l>
            <l>The <hi>Holy-one</hi> the all-knower, will not know.</l>
            <l>Shame and confuſion ſhall be-ſpread him ouer,</l>
            <l>Wiſhing the holes to hide, and hils to couer.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Iames 2.13. Reuel. 6.15.16</note>Eternall fire ſhall fry his thirſty veines;</l>
            <l>Immortall dying in eternall paines.</l>
            <l>His eyes, ſo nice to looke on Lazarus ſore</l>
            <l>Shall ſwim in ſulphury teares (tortur'd the more,</l>
            <l>To ſee aboue, in bliſſe and glory rife,</l>
            <l>Whom ruthleſſe here, he would not ſee, in life)</l>
            <l>His eares here deafe vnto deſtreſſed ones;</l>
            <l>Shall there heare horror of the damned grones;</l>
            <l>Nor ſhall the voyce of mercy him ſalute,</l>
            <l>Who, in effect, to needy moane was mute:</l>
            <l>Millions of maſſes cannot him redeeme,</l>
            <l>Nor all Church-treaſure euer ranſome him,</l>
            <l>From all-thought-paſſing pangs of wretchednes;</l>
            <l>As, endleſſe, caſeleſſe, and remedyleſſe.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOSVA SYLVESTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:9"/>
            <head>On Vſurers.</head>
            <l>OF all men vs'rers are not leaſt accurſt;</l>
            <l>They robbe the Spittle, pinch th' afflicted worſt:</l>
            <l>In others griefe they'r moſt delighted in;</l>
            <l>Whilſt Giuers ſuffer for the Takers ſinne:</l>
            <l>O how vniuſt a trade of life is that,</l>
            <l>Which makes the lab'rers, leane, and th' idle, fatte?</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>FRA. QVARLES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <l>FAEnere qui lucrum facit, eſt homicida Catoni,</l>
            <l>Furti dupla, huius quadrupla mulcta fuit.</l>
            <l>Non facit heredem, priuatur honore ſepulchri</l>
            <l>Qui tenues lucro faeneris auget opes.</l>
            <l>Sermo ſacer, patres, pius omnis damnat, at vna</l>
            <l>(Quae docet errores) Conſuetudo probat.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Iohannes Garbraudus</hi> Oxonienſis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:10"/>
            <head>To the Vſurer.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mors tua, mors Chriſti, fraus mundi, gloria caeli,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et dolor inferni, ſunt meditanda tibi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy death, the death of Chriſt, the worlds tentation.</l>
                  <l>Heauens ioy, hells torment, be thy meditation.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Three profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table helpes of a godly life. Pſal. 119.57 58, 59. See Bb. <hi>Cowper</hi> in Rom. 8.1.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here bee three moſt notable helpes of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life, deliuered to vs by</hi> Dauid, <hi>in three verſes of the</hi> 119 <hi>Pſalme,</hi> 57. O Lord, I haue determined to keepe thy Word. 58. I haue made my ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in thy preſence with my whole heart. 59. I haue conſidered my wayes, and turned my feete vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy teſtimonies. <hi>Determination is the firſt: It is a good thing by ſetled reſolution to conclude with thy ſelfe that thou wilt liue godly. Supplication is the ſecond: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept by continuall Prayer thy determination bee confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and ſtrengthned by grace from God, thy concluſions which thou takeſt to day, ſhall vaniſh to morrow. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is the third, and it is profitable to reduce thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the way of God, ſo often as of weakeneſſe thou
<pb facs="tcp:150798:10"/> thou wanders from it, contrary to thy firſt determination. Theſe are three helps to keepe thy heart in the way of God: ſo neceſſary, that if without them thou doſt any worke, it is not posſible but thou ſhalt be ſnared. Firſt therefore determine to forſake thy Vſury, and to make reſtitution. Secondly, ſtrengthen this determination by Prayer, ſay with</hi> Dauid, create in me a cleane heart, O God:<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.10. Pſal. 119.36</note> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new a right ſpirit within me. Encline my heart vnto thy teſtimonies: and not to couetouſneſſe. <hi>Thirdly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thy former courſes when thou waſt a theeuiſh Vſurer, and ſay with our bleſſed Sauiour:</hi> What is a man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, if he ſhall gaine the whole world,<note place="margin">Math. 16.26</note> and loſe his owne ſoule? Or what ſhall a man giue in exchange for his ſoule? <hi>Say with the holy Apoſtle</hi> S. <hi>Paul,</hi> they that will be rich, fall into temptation and a ſnare, and into many fooliſh and hurtfull luſts,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9.</note> which drowne men in perdition and deſtruction. Finally, doe good,<note place="margin">v. 18, 19.</note> be rich in good workes, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate, laying vp in ſtore for thy ſelfe a good foundation againſt the time to come, that thou mayſt lay hold on eternall life. <hi>Conſider what I ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>and the Lord giue thee vnderſtanding in all things, Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy remembrancer, <hi>I. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150798:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150798:11"/>
            <head>THE ENGLISH VSVRER.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the definition of Vſury.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He contract of Vſury is nothing elſe but illiberall mutuation,<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> in Pſ. 15. p. 151. Vſury defined.</note> and may thus brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be defined: Vſury is mutuation, or lending for gaine. This briefe defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth fully ſet forth the true nature of Vſury, and ſufficiently diſtinguiſheth it from all other contracts whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>FIrſt I ſay it is mutuation or lending,<note place="margin">Subiectum vſurae mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum.</note> which is alſo preſuppoſed in the Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25. and the ſame if need were, might be proued by the other relatiue, which is borrowing: for lending and borrowing are relatiues: And if he which taketh vp mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney vpon vſury, be a borrower; then he that giueth or putteth it forth vnto vſury, is a lender.</p>
               <p>The contract therefore of Vſury is a contract of len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: now in the contract of mutuation or lending,<note place="margin">Idem p. 152.</note> diuers
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150798:12"/> things concurre, which alſo belong to the nature of Vſury.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That it is of ſuch things as are ſpent in the vſe, and conſiſt in quantitie, that is to ſay in number, weight, or meaſure, as Money, and Victuals, Corne, Wine, Oyle, &amp;c. which are particularly mentioned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25.37.</item>
                  <item>2. And therefore is alienation not onely of the vſe, but alſo of the propertie, from which the vſe (of ſuch things as are ſpent in the vſe) cannot be ſeuered.</item>
                  <item>3: As the property is transferred to the borrower, ſo the borrower ſtandeth to the hazzard of the thing bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed.</item>
                  <item>4. That it is not a perpetuall alienation of that which is lent, but for a time, which time being expired, the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower is bound to reſtore the principall.</item>
                  <item>5. Becauſe the thing borrowed is to be ſpent in the vſe, therefore the borrower is bound, not to reſtore the ſelfe ſame particular which he borrowed, but ſo much in the ſame kind, or the ſame valew.</item>
                  <item>6. It belongeth to the nature of lending, that it be free and liberall. And this is that which followeth in the definition, as the difference to diſtinguiſh it from free lending, that it is for gaine.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vſury is for gaine.</note>By gaine is ment any addition, ouerplus, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, ouer and aboue the Principall, whether it bee money, or money worth, required not for the indemnity of the Creditour,<note place="margin">Idem p. 153. What is to be eſteemed gaine.</note> to ſaue him harmeleſſe, but for his aduantage, to make him a gainer by lending; for that onely is to be eſteemed gaine, which is an ouerplus,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150798:12"/> clearely gotten aboue the Principall. And whereas I ſay it is eyther money, or money worth: this money worth reacheth farre, not onely to goods and wares, but alſo to labours and ſeruices, and whatſoeuer elſe being va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable by money, may lawfully be let or ſold for money. And when I ſay that vſury is lending for gaine, it is ment, that in the firſt act of lending vpon vſury, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the forbearing, whereby that lending is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, gaine is, if not couenanted for, yet at the leaſt intended. So that where there is a couenant or intent of gaine by loane, whether it be in the firſt act of len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or afterwards in the forbearing, it is vſury: and contrariwiſe, where there is neyther a couenant nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of gaine in lending or forbearing, there is not vſury, though there be an ouerplus, or encreaſe receiued ouer and beſides the Principall.</p>
               <p>The Hebrew word <hi>Neſheh,</hi> is the ordinary name to ſignifie vſury, as <hi>Foenus</hi> in Latine, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Greeke,<note place="margin">Idem p. 154.</note> or Vſury in Engliſh. For the money which is lent vpon vſury, is called <hi>Neſheh,</hi> a biter, or which biteth:<note place="margin">The names of vſury.</note> and the Hebrew phraſe, which ſignifieth to be lent vpon vſury, is to bite, as appeareth plainely, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not lend vpon vſury to thy brother money or meat, or any thing elſe, Aſher Iſhak,</hi> which biteth, that is, which is lent vpon vſury. For whatſoeuer the Vſurer lendeth, it hath teeth, and iawes to eate and conſume the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of other men; his Corne or victuals which were made to be eaten, doe eate, and his money which was made to be ſpent, doth waſt the ſubſtance of others, and therefore Hebrew writers doe teach, that in the name of Vſury is encluded an admonition, not to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row vpon Vſury: for hee which taketh money vpon Vſury, taketh as it were a ſerpent into his boſome.</p>
               <p>This is confeſſed by <hi>Caluine</hi> himſelfe, that whereas
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150798:13"/> Vſurers auoyd the name <hi>Neſheh,</hi> which ſignified biting, as they doe the name Vſury among vs, as being odious, and therefore alledged, that they tooke not <hi>Neſheh</hi> but <hi>Tarbith,</hi> as amongſt vs they will not be thought to take Vſury, but conſideration, vſance, or intereſt: therefore the Lord forbideth as well <hi>Tarbith</hi> as <hi>Neſheh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Exod. 22.25 Levit. 25.36..</note> whereby he condemneth generally <hi>Quamlibet ſortis acceſſionem</hi> (ſayth <hi>Caluin</hi>) any addition or increaſe aboue the principall. And vpon <hi>Ezekiel</hi> chap. 18. he ſayth the Prophet condemneth not onely <hi>Neſheh</hi> which ſignifieth biting,<note place="margin">God forbids biting vſury and increaſe.</note> but alſo <hi>Tarbith,</hi> which he tranſlateth <hi>incrementum,</hi> increaſe: <hi>hoc est</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>quicquid lucri ſibi avari homines conciliant ex mutuo;</hi> that is, whatſoeuer gaine couetous men doe get to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by loane.</p>
               <q>Actuall Vſury is deſcribed by <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. FENTON,</hi> to be pactum ex mutuo lucrum.
<list>
                     <item>Lucre for loane vpon couenant; or</item>
                     <item>The couenant of lucre for lending: or</item>
                     <item>Lending vpon couenant for lucre.<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fenton</hi> Treatiſe of vſury, p. 15.</note>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </q>
               <p>So that theſe three words, <hi>mutuum, pactum, lucrum,</hi> doe define and circumſcribe the entire nature of that Vſury whereof the maine queſtion is made, whether it be lawfull or not.</p>
               <p>And to theſe deſcriptions of Vſury, agree thoſe of our moſt reuerend, and iudicious Diuines: <hi>vide.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Willet</hi> vpon <hi>Exodus,</hi> p. 509. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Smith</hi> in <hi>Willet</hi> vpon <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> p. 625. <hi>Perkins, Com<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> 8. Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> 18. Sermon vpon Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Pie,</hi> Vſuries Spright coniured, p. 4. <hi>Powels</hi> poſitions of Vſury, p. 4. Bb. <hi>Iewel,</hi> vpon 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> p. 113. <hi>Ameſius de conſcientia, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 44. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> Diſcourſe vpon Vſury, p. 85. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Moſſe,</hi> Arraignement and conuiction of Vſury, p. 31.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150798:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> The diſtinction of Vſury.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Vſury is eyther Inward and Mentall, or Outward and Actuall.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>MEntall Vſury is a lending for gaine without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, that is,<note place="margin">Mentall vſury. Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> in Pſ. 15. p. 168.</note> when the creditor onely inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and looketh for gaine by lending and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing his money, but doth not indent or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant with the borrower for gaine. And this may be called, the Vſury of the heart:<note place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note> for the law of God being ſpirituall, doth not onely reſtraine the hands, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man; but alſo the intent and purpoſe of the heart: inſomuch, that morall actions though in ſhew good, are to be iudged euill, if they proceed from an ill intent, and tend to an ill end: for he that intendeth euill, hath the like euill will with him that worketh euill: and he which by lending onely intendeth his owne gaine, he lendeth for gaine, and therefore, if actuall Vſury be euill, then the intent and purpoſe thereof is alſo euill.</p>
               <p>Outward and actuall Vſury is, when the creditour doth not onely intend certaine gaine by lending, but alſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenanteth for a certaine ſumme to be allowed him at a certaine time, or times. This in the Scriptures is called im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of Vſury, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25.<note place="margin">Idem p. 170.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not impoſe Vſury vpon him:</hi> Wherefore in actuall Vſury, a couenant is made for certaine gaine, and in that couenant the very forme of actuall Vſury conſiſteth: for which cauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150798:14"/> ſome doe call ſuch a contract, formall Vſury. And this couenant vſeth to be confirmed by obligation, eyther ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball, as bils and bonds, or reall, as pawnes, or mortgage; or perſonall, as ſuretiſhip; whereby the creditor is ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the receit, and the debtor bound for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both of the principall and alſo of the Vſury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs now ſee how by this definition Vſury is distinguiſhed from other contracts, and alſo other things which may ſeeme to haue ſome affinity therewith: for of the rest it is needleſſe to ſpeake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is therefore diſtinguiſhed</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Vſury diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed. 1 From all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts. Idem p. 157.</note>1. From all liberall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, as that of donation or free gift, of mutuation, or free lending to ſpend, of commodation, or free lending to vſe, becauſe they be free and liberall, but Vſury is illiberall and for gaine.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">2 From all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full buying</note>2. From all lawfull buying: becauſe in buying there is a perpetuall alienation of money, in Vſury but for a time.</item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">3 For letting to hire.</note>3. From lawfull Location or letting to hire: which is the rather to be obſerued, becauſe ſome imagine, that money and other things which are lent vpon Vſury,<note place="margin">Idem p. 158.</note> may as well be let as other things. But there is a great difference betwixt Vſury, and the lawfull contract of Location or letting. And firſt they differ in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Vſury is in thoſe things which are ſpent in the vſe, and conſiſt in quantity, ſtanding in number, weight and meaſure.</cell>
                        <cell>Location, is of ſuch things as are not ſpent in the vſe, neyther ſtand in number, weight and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150798:14"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The ſubiect of Vſury, are ſuch things as haue no fruitfull vſe in themſelues, but the gaine which is to be raiſed by imployment of them, is to be imputed to the induſtry and skill of the imployer.</cell>
                        <cell>The ſubiect of Location haue a fruitfull vſe in themſelues naturally.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The vſe of things lent vpon Vſury cannot be ſeuered, or reckoned apart from the property and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe they are ſuch things as are ſpent in the vſe, and therefore if you vſe them, you ſpend them.</cell>
                        <cell>The fruitfull vſe of things lent, may be ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and reckoned apart, and is valuable by it ſelfe, as of Lands, Goods, Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp;c. which remaine in the vſe vnſpent.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>In the contract of loane, whether free or vpon V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, the lender granteth to the borrower, not onely the vſe, but alſo the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the thing lent, from which the vſe of that, which we lend to be ſpent in the vſe cannot be ſeuered: hence it is called <hi>mutuum,</hi> becauſe by lending it is made <hi>ex meo tuum.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>In the contract of Loca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the letter granteth to him that taketh to hire the vſe onely of the things retaining the property to himſelfe.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150798:15"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Becauſe that which is the ſubiect of loane, and Vſury, is ſpent in the vſe, and is lent to be ſpent; therefore the borrower is bound to reſtore, not the ſame particular which he borrowed, but ſo much in quantity or full valew in the ſame kind, without any impairing, or diminution.</cell>
                        <cell>Becauſe, that which is the ſubiect of commodity and Location, is lent, and let, not to be ſpent, but onely to be vſed: therefore he that taketh the ſame to vſe, is bound to reſtore the ſelfe ſame particular, which for the moſt part is impay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and made worſe in the vſe.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>As in mutuation, and Vſury, the property is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated to the borrower, ſo with the property alſo the hazzard wholy appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the borrower: for the very contract of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation includeth in it an obligation, binding the borrower, that whatſoeuer becommeth of this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar which he borroweth, he ſhall reſtore the full va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew thereof at the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, in the ſame kind. And to this purpoſe the borrower maketh promiſe, either by word or writing, entreth into bonds, and ſtatutes, laying his goods to pawne, or his lands to mortgage, giueth ſureties, to aſſure and ſecure the creditor for the principall.</cell>
                        <cell>As in Location the vſe is communicated to the Hirer, but the Letter retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the property: ſo the thing, if it ſhall miſcarry without the default of the Hirer: belongeth to the Letter, and not to the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, becauſe it came for his hire, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.14. And it is a rule in law, to whom the hazzard appertaineth, to him the fruit and profit belongeth.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150798:15"/>
               <p>Where there is a Couenant to beare part of the loſſe, as well as to reape part of the gaine,<note place="margin">4 From the contract of Partnerſhip.</note> and this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, is neyther vſury, nor loane: but a lawfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract.</p>
               <p>Which in Latine is called <hi>Nauticum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5 From aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers vſury.</note> or <hi>Maritimum Foenus,</hi> and is a gaine or allowance made for money which is tranſported beyond the Seas, at the perill and hazard of the Creditor. This is not vnlawfull, prouided,<note place="margin">Idem p. 164. 165.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, that there be an aduenture or hazard in truth, and not in pretence onely; and alſo that the gaine be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the hazard.</p>
               <p>Which is a gratuitie or free gift,<note place="margin">6 From libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vſury</note> when the borrower finding himſelfe much benefited by the lenders curteſie, doth of his owne accord in teſtimony of his thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, freely giue to the lender, who neyther intended when he lent, nor expected whiles he forbore, any gaine; and much leſſe couenanted for it.</p>
               <p>From that which is called <hi>Vſura compeus ſatoria</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compencing vſury, which we call intreſt:<note place="margin">7 From recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pencing vſury. Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> in Pſ. 15 p. 166. Dr. <hi>Smith</hi> in <hi>Willet</hi> vpon Leuit. p. 631. <hi>Powels</hi> Poſit. of vſury p. 14. Bb. <hi>Iewel.</hi> 1 Theſſ. p. 135.</note> which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a iuſt recompence which the Debter, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing through his default beene the effectuall cauſe of the Creditours hinderance, doth owe vnto him by the Law of nature, and that hinderance may be two fold, <hi>Damnum emergens,</hi> loſſe ariſing, or <hi>Lucrum ceſſans,</hi> gaine ceaſing: but this ceaſing gaine which muſt come into eſtimation, muſt not be vncertaine and doubtfull, but certaine: or at leaſt very probable.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Here are certaine cautions to be remembred.</head>
                  <item n="1"> Firſt, that intreſt bee eſteemed not according to the gaine or benefit which the borrower hath had by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of the money, but according to the hinderance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150798:16"/> or loſſe which the creditour ſuſtained through the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers default.</item>
                  <item n="2"> Secondly, that Intereſt is not to he required <hi>niſi post moram,</hi> but onely after delay and default committed by the borrower.</item>
                  <item n="3"> Thirdly, that not alwayes after delay it is to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but onely then, when the creditour hath indeed ſuſtained loſſe or hindrance by the borrowers delay.</item>
                  <item n="4"> Fourthly, that he doe not voluntarily incurre any loſſe, meaning to lay the burthen thereof on the borrower, but doe his true endeauour to auoyd it, eyther in whole or in part.</item>
                  <item n="5"> Fiftly, that when he ſuſpecteth loſſe or hinderance by the debtors delay, he deſcend not into extremities with thoſe who haue broken day, not through negligence or vnfaythfulneſſe, but through want and neceſſity, which they did not foreſee: and let him remember, that where is no fault, there ought to be no puniſhment.</item>
                  <item n="6"> Sixtly, that the eſtimation of the intereſt be not referred to the creditors owne arbitrament, but committed to the iudgement of ſome other honeſt and diſcreet men: which conditions being obſerued, it is lawfull for the creditour to require an ouerplus beſides his principall: which ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus notwithſtanding is not vſury.</item>
               </list>
               <p>How vſury diſcovers it ſelfe in ſelling, in buying, in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, in partnerſhip and exchange, vnder pretence of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturers vſury, vnder the colour of recompencing vſury, <hi>vide.</hi> Bb. <hi>Downam,</hi> vpon the 15 Pſalme, p. 173, 175, 182, 183, 188, 191. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fentons</hi> Treatiſe of vſury, p. 21, 22, 23, 24, 25. <hi>Powels</hi> poſitions of vſury, in his Epiſtle Dedicatory. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Moſſe,</hi> in the Arraignement and Conniction of vſury, p. 62. to p. 68.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150798:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. 3. The Teſtimony of ſixe learned Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England</hi> concerning vſury.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Teſtimony of Biſhop Sands.</head>
                  <p>THis biting Worme of Vſury,<note place="margin">Sermon vpon 1 Sam. 12.23, 24. Vſury a biting worme, a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</note> that deuowring wolfe hath conſumed many, many it hath pulled vpon their knees, and brought to beggery: many ſuch as might haue lived in great wealth, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour not a few. This canker hath corrupted all England: we ſhall doe God and our country true ſeruice, by taking away this euill; repreſſe it by Law, elſe the heavy hand of God hangeth ouer vs, and will ſtrike vs.</p>
                  <p>God ſayth, Lend freely, and looke for no gaine:<note place="margin">Idem Sermon vpon Luke 1.74.75.</note> but will the Vſurer, whoſe money is his god, remit his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt becauſe of this; becauſe the Lord hath ſo charged him? No, he will not let goe his ten or twenty, or thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the hundred. To him the glory of God,<note place="margin">Note. Nothing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the Vſurer but money.</note> yea and his owne ſoule is vile, nothing is precious but onely his money. What the Prophet ſpeaketh of putting forth money to vſury, he full little regardeth, but ſeedeth ſtill vpon his maſt, and bleſſeth himſelfe when he waxeth fat, not perceiuing that God hath already plagued him with a plague of all plagues, the obduration of his heart. And although that God hath giuen him ouer into a dull and ſenceleſſe minde,<note place="margin">Vſurers haue hard hearts.</note> his eares being ſo damned vp that nothing can haue enterance to moue, or touch his hard heart, yet he ſtill bleſſeth himſelfe, and his accurſed ſoule. Thou Vſurer, thou idolater, that doſt glory in thy ſhame,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150798:17"/> in thy euill gotten gold:<note place="margin">Their wealth proſpers not.</note> doſt thou not know, that thy wealth ſhall melt like ſnow before the Sunne? Thinkeſt thou ſtill to hold it? O foole, this night ſhall they take away thy ſoule, perhaps this inſtant, and then whoſe is all this? After that <hi>Zacheus</hi> fell to the ſeruice of Chriſt, and that Chriſt entred into his houſe, he preſently forſooke the ſeruice of Mammon, made a large reſtitution of that which he had gained by ſuch vnlawfull meanes, and then began to be liberall: and not onely to lend freely, but to giue for nothing. He gaue the one halfe of all his goods to the poore. If God would at this day worke thus in the heart of one Zacheus, a rich Vſurer, how many poore might be relieued by ſuch a reſtitution? He might maintayne many a needy man, and ſaue his owne ſoule. Well, this one thing we know, the word that proceedeth out of Gods mouth againſt vſury,<note place="margin">Iſ. 55.11.</note> ſhall not returne in vaine, if it cannot worke reformation, it will worke confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  <p>Euery man is to his neyghbour a debtor, not onely of that which himſelfe borroweth,<note place="margin">Idem Sermon vpon Rom. 13.8, 9, &amp;c.</note> but of whatſoeuer his neyghbour needeth: a debtor, not onely to pay that he oweth, but alſo to lend that he hath and may conueniently ſpare; to lend I ſay according to the rule of Chriſt, <hi>Luke.</hi> 6. <hi>Lend looking for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereby.</hi> So that theſe ouer-payments, the vſury which hath ſpoyled and eaten vp many,<note place="margin">Vſury the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</note> the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the Commonwealth, is vtterly both forbidden to man, and abhorred of God. To bargaine for Lead, Graine, or Leaſes, with ſuch as haue neyther Lead, Graine, nor Leaſes to pay, neyther any ſuch matter meant, but onely vnlawfull gaine of money, the party to forfeit his obligation, becauſe he ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can, nor meaneth ſuch payment, and the lender not content to receiue leſſe aduantage then thirty at the hundred, this is but a patched cloake to couer this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150798:17"/> vild ſinne withall.<note place="margin">Note.</note> Whatſoeuer thou receiueſt vpon condition, or by what meanes ſoeuer thou receiueſt more then was lent, thou art an vſurer toward thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and God, will be a reuenger againſt thee. He whom thou ſhouldſt obey if thou wilt be ſaued,<note place="margin">Ezod. 22 25. Levit. 25 27. Deut. 23.19.</note> doth in expreſſe words command thee, not to lend thy money for vſury. This Word of God, man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſpence withall, and it ſhall not returne in vaine; if it cannot be a conuerting commandeme it, it ſhall be a confounding iudgement. The reaſons of men for vſury muſt giue place to the precepts of God againſt it.<note place="margin">The reaſons of men for vſury, muſt giue place to the precept of God againſt it.</note> What man art thou that wilt be wiſer then thy Maker? Hath God condemned it, and dareſt thou defend it? is it in his iudgement iniurious, and doth thy iudgement thinke it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall? Hath he ſeene reaſon to prohibit it, and doſt thou ſee reaſon why thou mayſt vſe it? ſuch reaſons with the makers and vſers of them, the Lords iuſtice ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy. And yet in truth all Nations, at all times haue condemned it, as the very bane and peſtilence of a Commonwealth:<note place="margin">The old Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vſury</note> whereof the old Romane both Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory and practiſe is an often witneſſe. Theſe ſecret ſhifts are ſeene of God, and abhorred, and will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged: well mayſt thou eſcape the hands of man by thy coloured deluſions, yet canſt thou not eſcape the ſharpe and ſwift iudgement of God:<note place="margin">Note.</note> who accordingly as hee hath threatned, will exclude thee out of his Kingdome, interdict thee his Tabernacle, and hurle thee into Hell: Where thy euill gotten money can neyther redeeme nor helpe thee, a iuſt reward for thy vniuſt vſury. Our Apoſtle requireth that we pay vnto euery man the thing that we owe, and we are as much debt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tors to lend freely, as others faythfully to pay the thing which was lent.</p>
                  <p>The bowels of compaſſion are in ſome men ſo mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualouſly dryed and cloſed vp,<note place="margin">Idem Sermon vpon Micah. 6 8 p. 100.</note> that they turne away their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150798:18"/> faces from all men, that deſire any thing at their hands, though they aske it not of gift,<note place="margin">Vſurers worſe then Iewes.</note> but of loane, vnleſſe they aske to buy the loane with Vſury. The Iewes euen till this day will not lend vpon vſury among themſelues, but lend freely to their brethren and without gaine. <hi>Iudas</hi> himſelfe that ſold his Maſter for money, was not more cruell hearted I ſuppoſe then theſe men are, who for money deuoure their brethren: their hearts are iron hearts, they haue no ſparke of pity or compaſſion left in them, let them not thinke but that one day their gaine ſhall be their exceeding loſſe.<note place="margin">Note.</note> If <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> thought that one euill got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten groat, layd vp amongſt a cheſt full of money, would be a canker to fret out and eate vp the reſt, what ſhall become then of ſo much gotten by ſo vnmercifull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly meanes? Where is loue, where is mercy, when lending of money is become merchandize? Enough hath beene ſayd in this place of this matter, which if it be not amended, be ye aſſured that the Lord God in his iuſt wrath will plague you both in your ſelues, and in your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2</hi> Teſtimony. Bb. Iewell.</head>
                  <p>MAny liue in vſury, a moſt filthy trade, a trade which God deteſteth,<note place="margin">Sermon vpon Rom. 13.12.</note> a trade which is the very ouerthrow of all Chriſtian loue: <hi>But their gaine ſhall be to their loſſe, and their money to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. He that giueth his mony vpon vſury, ſhall not dwell in the Tabernacle of the Lord, nor reſt vpon his holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Treatiſe vpon the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note>Deceiue no man by wrongfull dealing, increaſe not thy goods by extortion nor by vſury. <hi>He that giueth his money to vſury, ſhall not enter into the Tabernacle of the Lord. He that taketh vſury of his neyghbour, killeth him without a ſword, the Lord will auenge it.</hi> He will not bleſſe ill
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150798:18"/> gotten goodes, they cannot proſper: they will neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, nor remaine vnto the third heire.</p>
                  <p>Vſury is a kind of lending of money, or corne, or oyle,<note place="margin">vpon 1 Theſ. p. 113. Vſury defined.</note> or wine, or of any other thing, wherein, vpon couenant and bargaine, we receiue againe the whole principall which we deliuered, and ſomewhat more, for the vſe and occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying of the ſame: as if I lend 100 pound, and for it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant to receiue 105 pound, or any other ſumme, greater then was the ſumme which I did lend:<note place="margin">No good man an Vſurer.</note> this is that which we call vſury: ſuch a kind of barganing as no good man, or godly man euer vſed. Such a kind of barganing as all men that euer feared Gods iudgements haue alwaies ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred and condemned. It is filthy gaines,<note place="margin">Note. Vſurers ſay, Lord increaſe our fayth, and then make ſuch a confeſſion of it as Bb. Iewell doth in this place.</note> and a worke of darkeneſſe, it is a monſter in nature: the ouerthrow of mighty kingdomes, the deſtruction of flouriſhing States, the decay of wealthy Cities, the plagues of the world, and the miſery of the people: it is theft, it is the murthering of our brethren its the curſe of God, and the curſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This is Vſury. By theſe ſignes and tokens you may know it: For whereſoeuer it raigneth all thoſe miſchiefes enſue.</p>
                  <p>Whence ſpringeth Vſury? Soone ſhewed.<note place="margin">Idem p. 115. The cauſe of vſury.</note> Euen thence whence theft, murder, adultery, the plagues, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the people doe ſpring. All theſe are the workes of the diuell, and the workes of the fleſh.<note place="margin">Iohn 8. Vſurers of their father the diuell.</note> Chriſt telleth the Phariſees, <hi>You are of your father the diuell, and the luſts of your father you will doe.</hi> Euen ſo may it truely be ſayd to the Vſurer, Thou art of thy father the diuell, and the luſts of thy father thou wilt doe, and therefore thou haſt pleaſure in his workes. The diuell entered into the heart of <hi>Iudas,</hi> and put in him this greedineſſe, and couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of gaine, for which he was content to ſell his maſter. <hi>Iudas</hi> heart was the ſhop, the diuell was the foreman to worke in it. They that will be rich, fall into tentation and ſnares, and into many fooliſh and noyſome luſts,<note place="margin">1 Tim 6.9 10.</note> which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150798:19"/> drowne men in perdition and deſtruction. For the deſire of money, is the roote of all euill. And S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer committeth ſinne is of the Diuell.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.8. Thus we ſee that the diuell is the planter, and the father of vſury.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem p. 116. The fruits of vſury.</note>What are the fruits of vſury? <hi>A.</hi> 1. It diſſolueth the knot and fellowſhip of mankind. 2. It hardneth mans heart. 3. It maketh men vnnaturall, and bereaueth them of charity, and loue to their deareſt friends. 4. It bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth miſery and prouoketh the wrath of God from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. 5. It conſumeth rich men, it eateth vp the poore, it maketh bankrupts, and vndoeth many houſeholders, 6 The poore occupiers are driuen to flee, there wiues are left alone, their children are hopeleſſe, and driuen to beg their bread, through the vnmercifull dealing of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous vſurer.</p>
                  <p>He that is an Vſurer, wiſheth that all others may lacke and come to him and borrow of him:<note place="margin">Idem p. 120. Our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers abhorred vſury.</note> that all others may loſe, ſo that he may haue gaine. Therefore our old fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers ſo much abhorred this trade, that they thought an Vſurer vnworthy to liue in the company of Chriſtian men They ſuffered not an Vſurer to be a witneſſe in matters of Law. They ſuffer him not to make a Teſtament, and to beſtow his goods by Will. When an Vſurer dyed, they would not ſuffer him to be buried in places appointed for the buriall of Chriſtians. So highly did they miſlike this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull ſpoyling and deceiuing our brethren.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem p. 121. All profeſſions of men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne Vſury.</note>But what ſpeake I of the ancient Fathers of the Church? there was neuer any Religion, nor Sect, nor State, nor De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, nor Profeſſion of men, but they haue diſliked it. Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, Greekes, Latins, Lawyers, Diuines, Catholikes, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks; all Tongues, and Nations, haue euer thought an Vſurer as dangerous as a theefe. The very ſenſe of nature proues it to be ſo. If the ſtones could ſpeake, they would
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150798:19"/> ſay as much. But ſome will ſay,<note place="margin">Idem p. 124. The Vſurers obiection.</note> all kindes of vſury are not forbidden, there may be caſes where vſury may ſtand with reaſon and equity, and herein they ſay ſo much as by wit may be deuiſed, to paint out a ſoule and vgly idoll, and to ſhadow themſelues in manifeſt and open wickedneſſe. Whatſoeuer God ſayth, yet this or this kind of vſury, ſay they, which is done in this or this ſort, is not forbidden. It profiteth the Commonwealth, it relieueth great numbers, the poore ſhould otherwiſe periſh, none would lend them.</p>
                  <p>By like good reaſon,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer.</note> there are ſome that defend theft and murder, they ſay, there may be ſome caſe, where it is lawfull to kill or to ſteale: for God willed the Hebrews to rob the Aegyptians, and <hi>Abraham</hi> to kill his owne ſonne <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac.</hi> In theſe caſes the robbery and the killing of his ſonne were lawfull. So ſay they.<note place="margin">Some pleade for Vſurers, as Papiſts for whores.</note> Euen ſo by the like reaſon doe ſome of our countreymen maintayne concubines, curti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans, and brothel-houſes, and ſtand in defence of open ſtewes. They are (ſay they) for the benefit of the Country, they keepe men from more dangerous inconueniences, take them away, it will be worſe. Although God ſay, There ſhall be no whore of the daughters of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> neither ſhall there be a whore-keeper of the ſonnes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Yet theſe men ſay all manner of whoredome is not forbidden. In theſe and theſe caſes it is not amiſſe to alow it.</p>
                  <p>As <hi>Samuel</hi> ſayd to <hi>Saul,</hi> ſo may we ſay to the Vſurer?<note place="margin">Idem p. 126. God cares not for Vſurers excuſes.</note> thou haſt deuiſed caſes and colours to hide thy ſhame, but what regard hath God to thy caſes? What careth he for thy reaſons? the Lord would haue more pleaſure, if when thou heareſt his voyce thou wouldeſt obey him. For what is thy deuice againſt the counſell, and ordinance of God? What bold preſumption is it for a mortall man to controule the Commandements of immortall God? And to weigh his heauenly wiſedome in the ballance of humane fooliſhneſſe? When God ſayth, thou ſhalt not take vſury, what creature of GOD art thou which canſt take vſury? When God maketh
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150798:20"/> it vnlawfull,<note place="margin">They are of a deſperate mind.</note> what art thou, oh man, that ſayſt, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? This is a token of a deſperate mind. It is found true in thee, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſayd, the loue of money is the roote of all ill. Thou art ſo giuen ouer vnto the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Mammon, that thou careſt not to doe the will of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem p. 144.</note>Thus much I thought expedient to ſpeake of the loathſome and foule Trade of vſury, I know not what fruit will grow thereby, and what it will worke in your hearts. If it pleaſe God, it may doe that good that I wiſh. I haue done my duety, I call God for a record vnto my ſoule, I haue not deceiued you. I haue ſpoken vnto you the truth. If I be deceiued in this matter, O God thou haſt deceiued me. Thou ſayſt, <hi>Thou ſhalt take no vſury.</hi> Thou ſayſt, <hi>He that taketh increaſe, ſhall not liue.</hi> What am I, that I ſhould hide the words of my God, or keepe them backe from the hearing of his people? The Learned old Fathers haue taught vs, it is no more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to take vſury of our brother, then it is to kill our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They that be of God heare this, and conſider it, and haue a care that they diſpleaſe him not. But the wicked that are no whit moued, and care not what God ſayth, but caſt his Word behind them: which haue eyes and ſee not, and eares yet heare not: becauſe they are filthy, they ſhall be filthy ſtill: their greedy deſire ſhall increaſe to their confuſion, and as their money encreaſeth, ſo ſhall they encreaſe the heapes of their ſinnes.<note place="margin">Note.</note> Pardon me if I haue beene long or vehmeent, of thoſe that are Vſurers I aske no pardon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem p. 145.</note>I heare that there are certaine in this City which wallow wretchedly in this filthineſſe, without repentance, I giue them warning in the hearing of you all,<note place="margin">Vſury a cruell and deteſtable ſinne.</note> and in the preſence of God, that they forſake this cruell and deteſtable ſin. If otherwiſe, they continue therein, I will open their ſhame,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150798:20"/> and denounce Excommunication againſt them,<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Iewel</hi> threatneth excomuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation againſt Vſurers.</note> and publiſh there names in this place, before you all. That you may know them, and abhorre them, as the plagues and monſters of the world: that if they be paſt all feare of God, they may yet repent and amend for worldly ſhame.</p>
                  <p>Tell me thou wretched wight of the World, thou vnkind creature which art paſt all ſenſe and feeling of God, which knoweth the will of God,<note place="margin">Vſurers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent. 1 Becauſe they come to Church. 2 Becauſe they read GODS Word. 3 Becauſe they come into the company of good men. They cauſe Gods wrath to fall vpon their children.</note> and doſt the contrary? How dareſt thou come into the Church? It is the Church of that GOD, which hath ſayd, thou ſhalt take no vſury, and thou knoweſt he hath ſo ſayd. How dareſt thou read or heare the Word of God? It is the Word of that God, which condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vſury; and thou knoweſt he doth condemne it. How dareſt thou come into the company of thy brethren? vſury is the plague and deſtruction and vndoing of thy brethren. And this thou knoweſt. How dareſt thou looke vpon thy Children? Thou makeſt the wrath of GOD fall downe from Heauen vpon them. Thy iniquity ſhall bee puniſhed in them to the third and forth Generation. This thou knoweſt. How dareſt thou looke vp into Heauen? Thou haſt no dwelling there: thou ſhalt haue no place in the Tabernacle of the higheſt. This thou knoweſt. Becauſe thou robbeſt the poore, deceiueſt the ſimple, and eateſt vp the Widowes Houſes: therefore ſhall thy Children bee naked, and begge their bread: therefore ſhalt thou and thy riches periſh together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The third Teſtimonie, Biſhop King.</head>
                  <p>HOw long will the Vſurer and oppreſſor of others whoſe Lawes are as kniues,<note place="margin">Vpon Ionas p. 90.</note> and whoſe teeth be of iron, ſleepe in his bed of miſchiefe, as the Pſalmiſt calleth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150798:21"/> it, and in the contemplation and ſolace of his ill gotten goods?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem p. 444. Lecture 32.</note>How long haue we cried againſt oppreſſions, and ſmitten the oppreſſours with the rod of Gods vengeance, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſmote the Rocke? And yet what one drop of remorſe haue we euer wrung from their ſtony hearts? How long haue we clapt our hands at the ſhameleſſe vſury of this place?<note place="margin">Miniſters muſt preach againſt vſury.</note> If vſury bee too ſtiffe to bee moued, yet we muſt free our ſoules, and if it were poſſible, we would alſo free them that are wrapt in their ſnares. If they little eſteeme the warning of the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth <hi>Pſalme,</hi> that giue their money vpon vſury, let them at leaſt take heede that receiue it. Let them not trie to beare an Oxe vpon their ſhoulders, when they are vnable to beare a Goate. That is, if pouerty be burthen enough vnto them, let them not adde the burthen of vſury. They aske what they ſhall doe? Doſt thou aske? Saith <hi>Plutarke.</hi> Thou haſt a tongue, begge. Thou haſt hands, worke. Thou haſt feete, walke. Thou haſt an heart,<note place="margin">Plutarch de vſura. <hi>Nihil tam moleſtum quam red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi> Idem p. 504. Lecture 37.</note> thinke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nauiga, renauiga,</hi> ſale forward and backeward, take any paynes, rather then to fall into the mercy of an Vſurer. There is nothing ſo bitter as to reſtore.</p>
                  <p>I would our Vſurers would marke this, that of all thoſe grieuous offences whereof <hi>Nineueh</hi> had labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a long time, the reſt are held a ſleepe, and their names ſpared, as not worthy in compariſon to come in ſpeech with their farre ſuperiour iniquity; onely the wickedneſſe of their hands,<note place="margin">Nam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> meos nec aequos mihi nec ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puere iuven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos Plutar. de uitando aere alieno.</note> which is not leaſt in bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the poore, is remembred and reported in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall wordes. Spake I of Vſurers? There are none: neyther is there a Sunne in the Skie. For mine owne part, I know them not. For they haue taken ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Horſe nor Bullocke of mee. But for my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns ſake both in the City and Country, I wiſh that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150798:21"/> their billes and bonds were all heaped together in the Market place, and ſet on fire, as they were ſometimes at <hi>Athens,</hi> that wee might all ioy and ſay, as <hi>Alcibiades</hi> then did, we never ſaw a clearer fire.<note place="margin">Nunquam vidi ignem purionem.</note> But becauſe we cannot eaſe our hearts ſo ſoone of them, nor by ſuch meanes I will tell them for their owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort what they ſhall truſt to amongſt other things that although they labour in the fire to get riches, yet the time ſhall come, when there ſhall nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vnto them but this, that they ſhall be able to know and recount with themſelues, how many debters they haue quite vndone: As for their treaſures of iniquity, let them plainely vnderſtand that they put them into a bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe bag which could hold nothing.<note place="margin">De malè quaeſitis, &amp;c.</note> Ill gotten goods ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deſcend to the third heire; perhaps, not to the ſecond, nor firſt, not to benefit himſelfe, who thinketh he hath moſt handfaſt. <hi>She gathered it of the hire of an harlot,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Micah 1. Vſurers goods ſhall not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> 
                     <hi>and it ſhall returne to the wages of an harlot.</hi> They gathered their wealth by vſury, and vſury or ſomewhat elſe ſhall conſume it. <hi>Gni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho</hi> the Vſurer as <hi>Lucian</hi> reporteth, lieth in hell, bemoaning his hard eſtate, that <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>docares</hi> an inceſtuous ſpend thrift ſhould waſte his goods: ſo may theſe, but I leaue their iudgement to God, to whom it belongeth. For vengeance is his, and he will repay it. Yet dare I giue ſentence againſt it, as far as the ancient Romanes lawes did: wherein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a thiefe was bound to make reſtitution of double, the Vſurer of foure fold. Their meaning is plaine enough,<note place="margin">Vſury double theft.</note> that they eſteemed vſury a double theft, and that at the leaſt is my iudgement. And therefore as <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi> made an Act, that none ſhould ſalute the Emperour,<note place="margin">Note.</note> who knew himſelfe to be a thiefe, ſo let our Vſurers, take them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues warned,<note place="margin">Vſurers not to ſalute Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> and diſcharged (ſo long as their hearts accuſe them of their double and treble theft) from ſaluting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and much more from eating, drinking, conuerſing, moſt of all from praying, faſting, communicating with Chriſtians.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150798:22"/>
                  <head>The <hi>4.</hi> Teſtimony, Biſhop Lakes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">In his workes vol. p. 343.</note>THis is no ſmall difference betweene God and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. The diueil in ſhew, biddeth vs, loue our ſelues, doe all for our ſelues, and we are ſo ſimple as to beleeue him,<note place="margin">The diuell the image of Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</note> and thinke that we doe ſo; whereas the euent proues that we doe all for him, and to our owne ruine: for he is the plaine image of Vſurers, who liue by the ſweat of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens browes, and cunningly grow rich by vndoing others with a ſeeming reliefe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem vpon Pſ. 50.21. God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue Vſurers.</note>God himſelfe ſayth it in the cloſe of this Pſalme, <hi>Heare this all ye that forget God.</hi> Iewes, Gentiles, whatſoeuer you be, if you be adulterers, drunkards, Vſurers, blaſphemers, any way wicked liuers, <hi>Conſider this</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>lest I ſuddenly take you away, and there be none to helpe you.</hi> For if we be guilty of ſuch ſinnes, and encourage our ſelues in them by baſe conceits of God, God will not faile to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue vs, and marſhall ſuch wickedneſſe before vs, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uict vs thereof, and to confound vs therewith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem Sermon vpon Iohn 2.16. Vſurers fill the land with poore.</note>While the Gentleman depopulates the Countrey, and the Vſurer and Victuler are become the chiefe Tradeſmen of Incorporations, what wonder if contrary to Gods Law, and the Kings, the whole Land be filled with miſerable poore.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The fift Teſtimony, Biſhop Downam.</head>
                  <p>This most reuerend and learned Biſhop proues vſury to be vnlawfull by diuers arguments.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="argument">
                     <head>1 <hi>Argument.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Propoſition.</hi> vpon Pſ. 13. p. 250.</note>Whatſoeuer peruerteth and ouerturneth an act of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, eſpecially ſuch a neceſſary act to humane ſocieties, that is to ſay, free lending: it is not onely a vice, but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable vice.</p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150798:22"/>
                     <p>But vſury peruerteth and depraueth this neceſſary act of liberality and charity, (free lending:<note place="margin">Aſſumpt.</note>) turning it into an act of ſelfe loue, couetouſneſſe and cruelty.</p>
                     <p>Therefore vſury is not onely a vice,<note place="margin">Concl.</note> but a deteſtable vice.</p>
                     <p>The propoſition is proued, becauſe nothing is oppoſite to vertue but vice. As for free lending, it is a commendable act of liberality, and a neceſſary duty of charity.</p>
                     <p>The aſſumption is cleare and manifeſt. For whereas by the ordinance of God and by the Law of nature, lending is free and charitable, intending the good of the borrower, and not of the lender; vſury hath made it illiberall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable, intending the lenders profit chiefly, if not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſeeking, yea couenanting for the lenders gaine as well out of the loſſe of the borrower as out of his gaine. The property of charity is not to ſeeke her owne, but the good of others, and whereas other vertues ſerue for the good of the ſubiect wherein they are, the acts of charity and liberality are referred to the good of others:<note place="margin">Note.</note> lending therefore being an act of liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and charity, ought to reſpect the good of the borrower, if not onely, yet chiefly; but lending by vſury is made an act of ſelfeloue, wherein the good of the borrower is ſought either not at all, or but in a ſecondary reſpect,<note place="margin">Vſurers coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for gaine.</note> as it ſerueth to further the lenders gaine. For indeed the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by vſury couenanteth abſolutely for gaine, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſometimes out of the borrowers loſſe, and ſometimes alſo out of his gaine, which the Vſurer will pretend to ſeeke and reſpect, but the truth is, he will neuer looke after his neighbours profit, vnleſſe therein he may be ſure to find his owne gaine.</p>
                     <p>The vſurers lending therefore is an act of ſelfeloue,<note place="margin">Lending pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from 3 fountaines.</note> and it is alſo an act of couetouſneſſe. For whereas lending pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from one of theſe 3 fountaines, either from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity, or from ciuill loue and humanity, or from couetouſneſſe: he is ſayd to lend in Chriſtian charity, who
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150798:23"/> lendeth for the Lords ſake to his needy neighbour, looking for nothing againe: in ciuill charity or curteſie, who len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to pleaſure his friend, looking for his owne againe: in couetouſneſſe who lookes for more then his owne. For indeed what is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that is couetouſneſſe, but an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull deſire of hauing more.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="argument">
                     <head>2 <hi>Argument.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Idem p. 310.</note>Vſury cannot be practiſed with a good conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot be done in fayth, that is to ſay, in a ſound perſwaſion out of the Word of God, that it is lawfull: and whatſoeuer is not of fayth is ſinne.<note place="margin">Rom. 14.23.</note>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="argument">
                     <head>3 <hi>Argument.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Phil. 4.8. Rom. 12.17. 1 Theſ. 5.22:</note>That which is not honeſt and of good report, is not to be practiſed. For the Scripture teacheth vs, that we ſhould doe ſuch things as are honeſt, and of good report, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for honeſt things, not onely before God, but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, abſtaining from all ſhewes of euill.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Improban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turij quaeſtus qui in odia hominum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currunt vt faeneratorum De Off. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note>But vſury is a very odious thing, and of ill report: the very heathen by the light of nature deteſted it. <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, ſuch things are to be miſliked which are odious, as namely that of Vſurers. <hi>Columella</hi> ſayth, that vſury is odious euen to thoſe whom it ſeemeth to helpe. <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſayth it is hated moſt worthily, &amp;c. As for Chriſtians, vſury in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time was ſo odious among them, that if any were but ſuſpected to be an Vſurer, his houſe was counted the houſe of the diuell, no neighbour would fetch fire at his houſe, or haue any thing to doe with him, children would poynt at him in the ſtreets: yea, by the lawes of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians they are diffamed perſons.<note place="margin">vid, Cent. 12. cap. 4. The vſurers houſe called the houſe of the diuell.</note> The Scriptures cenſure vſury as an abomination; that is, as a ſinne to be abhorred. and Pſ. 109.11. the holy Ghoſt vſeth this interpretation againſt the wicked: Let the exactour (meaning thereby the vſurer, as all Tranſlations, almoſt, beſides ſome Engliſh doe read) enſnare all that he hath. Whereby it may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, both that to be an Vſurer is an odious thing, and that it is a curſe to fall into his ſnare.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150798:23"/>
                     <p>Seing therefore vſury is and alwayes hath beene a thing ſo odious and of ſo bad report,<note place="margin">The Vſurer denies the concluſion.</note> no Chriſtian can practiſe it with a good conſcience.</p>
                     <p>The Vſurer ſinnes againſt God, his neighbour, and himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Firſt againſt God by impiety and vngodlineſſe.<note place="margin">Leuit 25.36. Neh. 5.9.</note> For the Vſurer wants the feare of God.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 He diſobeyeth the Commandements of GOD,<note place="margin">Idem p. 270.</note> ſtraightly commanding free loane, and ſharpely forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vſury, and contemneth the threatnings of God denounced againſt the ſame.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 He ſinnes by infidelity,<note place="margin">Vſurers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels.</note> in not beleeuing the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes of God made to thoſe who lend freely: for as <hi>Chryſost.</hi> hath well ſaid <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, vſury is the ofspring of infidelity.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 By diffidence, ending commonly in prophaneſſe. For the Lord would haue our faith concerning ſpirituall bleſſings in heauenly things,<note place="margin">Page 271.</note> to be excerciſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by our affiance repoſed in his goodneſſe for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bleſſings in earthly things, as may be gathered by the order of the fourth and fifth petitions of the Lords Prayer.<note place="margin">The vſurers dare not truſt to Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence.</note> — But the Vſurers whole endeuour is to ſettle himſelfe and his eſtate as it were out of the gunſhot of Gods prouidence: he will not deale by husbandry, or traffique becauſe of the hazards whereunto eyther of both is ſubiect: that is to ſay, becauſe of his diffidence in God, to whoſe prouidence he dare not truſt his goods: and therefore he will make ſure worke for himſelfe, that he ſhall not neede to ſtand to Gods courteſie. The practice of vſury ſhall bee as a Tower of <hi>Babel</hi> vnto him,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that whether GOD do bleſſe the traffique of men, or not, or whether it goe well or ill with Husbandrie, hee will bee ſure both of his Principall and of his gaine. All is one to him, whether the Marchants gaine or looſe, ſinke or ſwime, whether there bee Fammine or plenty faire.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150798:24"/> weather or foule, hee feareth no flouds In a word, his chiefe endeuour is, that in reſpect of worldly things hee may haue nothing to doe with God; and ſo at length of a faithleſſe man hee becommeth alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaine,<note place="margin">Ezeh. 22.12.</note> hauing forgotten God, as for this ſinne the Lord chargeth <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> neyther is God, I meane the true God in all his thoughts; for his god <hi>Mammon</hi> doth wholy poſſeſſe his heart.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Vſurers idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note>The Vſurer ſinneth by Idolatrie. For ſeeing the roote of vſury is couetouſneſſe (which is the roote of all euill) it cannot bee denied; but that euery Vſurer is couetous; and euery couetous man is an idolater <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.5. And a Seruant of <hi>Mammon, Mat.</hi> 6.24. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no true Seruant of the Lord, now you muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that for couetous perſons and idolaters, there is no inheritance in Heauen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Idem p. 232. The Vſurer is both vniuſt &amp; vncharitable.</note>Secondly, the Vſurer ſinneth againſt his neighbour for whereas there are two duties eſpecially to be practiſed towards our neighbour, that is to ſay, Iuſtice and Charity: Iuſtice, to giue euery man his owne, and Charity, not to ſeeke our owne but other mens profit Iuſtice: to do no wrong, Charity, to do good to all; vſury offendeth againſt both, as being both vniuſt and vncharitable. Which copulation is duely to be marked. For whereas ſome alledge,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that vſury is not againſt Charity, when ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the lender nor borrower is hurt thereby, it ſhall hereby appeare, that if at any time it may ſeeme not to be oppoſed to Charity as an hurtfull thing, yet it is alwayes oppoſed as an vniuſt and vnequall thing. For firſt, the generall Law both of Iuſtice and Charity is this, as you would that men ſhould do to you, ſo do you to them likewiſe.<note place="margin">See the anſwer to obiect. 2.</note> But when you haue neede to borrow, you would that Men ſhould lend you freely, and not impoſe Vſury vpon you: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in like caſe, when others would borrow of you in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150798:24"/> their neceſſity, you ought to lend them freely, and not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vſury vpon them.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, the Vſurer ſinneth againſt himſelfe by deſperate folly.<note place="margin">Idem p. 272. The vſurer ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againſt himſelfe.</note> For as euery notorious Malefactor may truly be ſaid to caſt away himſelfe, and is guilty of ſelfe-murder, as it is ſaid of <hi>Korah</hi> and his complices, <hi>Num.</hi> 16.38. ſo the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer likewiſe pulleth vpon himſelfe the fearefull iudgements. of God, and is guilty of his owne ouerthrow. For the Lord hath threatned not onely the tranſlation of their goods from them in this world, <hi>Pro,</hi> 28.8. but alſo, as touching the world to come, that they ſhall not dwell in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Gods holineſſe (as may be gathered out of the 15 Pſalme) but that they ſhall die the death, meaning therby the death of the ſoule.<note place="margin">Ezeh 18.13.</note>) and that you may know to whom the cauſe of the Vſurers damnation is to be imputed, it is added, and his blood ſhall be vpon him. And that is it which <hi>Leo</hi> ſaith, <hi>Poenus pecuniae, funus eſt animae,</hi> the gaine of vſury is the graue of the ſoule.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>6.</hi> Teſtimony, Biſhop Babington.</head>
                  <p>THere be great ſlyes, and thoſe be great men,<note place="margin">Vpon Exod. Ch. 8. p. 203.</note> that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannouſly rule, not ſhearing but ſhauing to the very skin, if they take not skin and all. And there be leſſer flies, and thoſe be Vſures, and other biting binders, who with their <hi>Nouerint vniuerſi,</hi> make an vniuerſall ruine of many a mans eſtate, and doe fetch him in ſtill with The conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this obligation, that in the end his condition is wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and his heart breaketh with the bitter griefe of Be it knowne to all men: Surely theſe are curſed flies indeed, the ſuckers of our ſap, the bibbers of our blood,<note place="margin">Vſurers be cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed flies.</note> the pinchers of our hearts, and the ſtingers and wringers of our very ſoules. The Aegyptian flies was nothing like vnto them, but yet you ſee was a great plague of God, ſent to puniſh the ſinnes of men. But let them remember that theſe flies of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150798:25"/> Aegypt had but a time, God ſent them in wrath, and tooke them away in mercy, vpon intreatie. Some <hi>Moſes</hi> or other ſhall ſtand vp, and the Lord ſhall ſend a ſtrong Weſt wind, to take theſe canker wormes away, and caſt them into the red Sea, that in our coaſt they may torment no longer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem vpon the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments p. 69. 70.</note>If a man (ſaith the Law) borrow any thing of his neighbour, and it be hurt or elſe die, the owner of it not being by, he ſhall ſurely make it good. If it be an hired thing he ſhall not make it good, for it came for his hire. In which Law, if we well weighe it we may firſt ſee, that if we haue that thing which our neighbour would borrow, and we be able, without our hurt, well to ſpare it him, we are bound to do it, or elſe we ſinne againſt this Law of GOD, and we euen ſteale from our brother, that which in right is his. For God would not euer haue made a Law for recompence of the lender,<note place="margin">It is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duty of loue to lend when we may.</note> if his thing lent receiue any harme, vnleſſe it had beene a neceſſary duty of loue to lend when we may: therefore this narrowneſſe of heart, and vnkind diſpoſition, to grudge vnto any that good which by lending wee can poſſibly do him, it is hatefull in the eyes of God, and a plaine breach of this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, in this Law, (as one hath very well noted,) wee may ſee a great light giuen to that hard controuerſie concerning vſury of money. For marke I pray you, how he ſaith in plaine termes, that if the thing were hired, and though it periſhed in the vſe, yet ſhould it not be made good by him which hired it, for it came for his hire. The money which Vſurers giue out, is hired as you know. Therefore if it were a thing that might be hired, you ſee the ſentence of God, though it periſhed.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150798:25"/>
                  <p>Secondly, marke againe how the Lord ſayth, though a man lend of meere loue freely without any hire, yet ſhall his recompence be nothing more, then good will againe, vnleſſe it die, or be hurt which he lendeth. Now money neyther dyeth, neyther commonly is any whit hurt, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth euery way as good as it came.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, conſider how the Law will haue an apparent hurt of the thing lent, or elſe it alloweth no recompence,<note place="margin">Vſurers haue conſideration for likely loſſe.</note> but Vſurers wil haue conſideration for likely loſſe: for, ſay they, If I had had my money, poſſibly I could haue gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thus much with it: yet are they not ſure they could haue done it, for God could haue croſſed their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and being not ſure that they could haue gained, it is not apparent that they haue beene hindred: but this Law of God prouideth in equity onely for apparent harme, and therefore nothing for them.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the equity of this Law is onely this, that good will be no loſer,<note place="margin">They will haue certaine gaine.</note> and therefore prouiſion is made for recompence, if the thing lent receiued hurt. But Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers will haue their good will, as they call it, certaine and an exceſſiue gainer.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, in this law of God, the borrower is reſpected, that he ſhould haue helpe of his neyghbour,<note place="margin">Vſury regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth wholy the lender, Vſury plaine iniury voyd of loue.</note> and not pay for it, vnleſſe he hurt the thing which he borrowed, but vſury regardeth wholy the lender. Wherefore it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that if this Law of God had euer any equity, this Vſury of money had euer plaine iniury, and that this kind of lending is voyd of loue, and therefore apparantly a breach of this Commandement.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150798:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4. The iudgement of our moſt Learned and Orthodox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Diuines concerning vſury.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The firſt Teſtimony, Doctor Willet.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">vpon Exodus, p. 509. vſury defined.</note>BEfore the ſeuerall poynts belonging to this queſtion can be diſcuſſed, firſt we muſt ſee what vſury is 1. <hi>Plus ex mutuo velle, quàm mutuatum ſit, iniquum est,</hi> to deſire more by lending, then was lent is wicked, <hi>Caietan.</hi> 2. <hi>Vſura eſt lucrum quod accipitur, ſolius mutuationis cauſa.</hi> Vſury is a gaine, which is taken onely for lending. <hi>Vrſinus. Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid lucri praeter ſortem dabatur,</hi> what gaine ſoeuer was giuen beſide the principall: whereupon it is called in the Hebrew <hi>Tarbith,</hi> that is, encreaſe of the multiplying. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin.</hi> 3. After the ſame manner was vſury defined in former times; as <hi>Carthag.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Nullus clericorum amplius acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piat, quam cuiquam accomodavit,</hi> that none of the cleargy ſhould receiue more then he hath lent. <hi>Augustine</hi> thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth an vſurer, <hi>Si plus quam dediſti, expectas accipere, fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerator es,</hi> if thou looke to receiue more, then thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, thou art an Vſurer.</p>
                  <p>That this kind of vſury is vtterly vnlawfull, and not to be practiſed among Chriſtians, it ſhall appeare by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Vſury condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. vnlawfull to the Iews.</note>Firſt, the Hebrews were forbidden to take any vſury at all of their brethren; of the Gentiles they might: but now <hi>diruta eſt maceries,</hi> the wall of partition is taken away, there is neither Iew nor Gentile, but all are one in Chriſt. <hi>Caluin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Of it ſelfe hurtfull.</note>Secondly, <hi>Vſura ex ſuo genere nociua eſt,</hi> Vſury euen of it ſelfe is hurtfull, becauſe it is called <hi>Neſheh,</hi> biting, <hi>Caietan.</hi> And the law of nature teacheth: that we ſhould not doe that to another, which we would not haue offered to our ſelues.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150798:26"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, vſury was deteſtable among the Heathen,<note place="margin">Deteſtable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</note> much more odious ought it to be among Chriſtians: as <hi>Cato</hi> being asked what it was to play the Vſurer, anſwered, <hi>Idem quod occidere;</hi> all one, as to kill: and further hee ſaid, that in former time, they vſed to puniſh a theefe but in two fold, an Vſurer in foure fold. <hi>Caluine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, vſury is againſt the firſt inſtitution of money,<note place="margin">Againſt the firſt inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of money.</note> 
                     <hi>Pecunia inuenta est, &amp;c.</hi> Money was inuented, and found out, that thereby things neceſſary for the maintenance of this like might bee prouided: but now it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and abuſed to couetouſneſſe, that money may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe money.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Vſury againſt Scripture.</note> the Scripture abſolutely condemneth vſury <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Ezeh.</hi> 18.17. And <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth, <hi>Vſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ſuper omnes mercatores maledictus,</hi> the Vſurer is accurſed beyond all Merchants and trading men.<note place="margin">Hom 38. ſup. Math.</note> And hee further vſeth this compariſon, like as when one ſifteth Wheate or any other graine in a ſieue,<note place="margin">Vſurers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</note> all the graine by little and little ſlippeth thorow, and ſo, <hi>Solum stercus remanet in cribro,</hi> onely the ſoile and durt remaineth in the ſieue:<note place="margin">An excellent compariſon.</note> ſo of all the ſubſtance and ill gotten goods of Vſurers, <hi>Nihil remanet praeter pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum,</hi> nothing remaineth beſide ſinne, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>If it be Obiected,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiect.</note> that God permitted the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes to take vſury of the Gentiles, therefore it was not ſimply vnlawfull: to this it may bee Anſwered,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> that they were thoſe ſeuen Nations of the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> of whom they might take vſury, which Nations they were commanded to deſtroy: and ſo by this meanes they might weaken their eſtate, and empoueriſh them: whereupon <hi>Ambroſe</hi> inferreth, <hi>Ab hoc vſuram exige, quem non ſit crimen occidere.</hi> Exact vſury of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150798:27"/> him, whom it is not vnlawfull to kill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiection. p. 511, 112.</note>But Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> hath certaine conſiderations, which make the receiuing of ſome gaine by the loane of money, not vnlawfull.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer.</note>Obſerue his conſiderations dilligently, and thou wilt vtterly diſlike thy vſurious practiſes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, if thou lend thy money vpon vſury, thou muſt not be ſuch a one as maketh it thy trade to liue by letting of money.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, thou muſt not lend money vpon vſury to thoſe of the poorer ſort: for to ſuch it is ſimply forbidden to lend vpon vſury, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22, 25, and that which he allowes, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly no vſury, (as he ſayth:) but rather a gratuity, that he which hath gained by anothers money, ſhould, to ſhew his thankefull mind, make him, which was the occaſion thereof, a reaſonable partaker of his gaine, <hi>Gratitudo animi lege naturali mandatur:</hi> this gratitude and thankfulneſſe of mind is commanded euen by the law of nature.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the intereſt which thou receiueſt muſt be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate not exceſſiue.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, this conſideration which thou receiueſt for the loane of money, muſt not be <hi>ex pacto,</hi> it muſt not be agreed vpon by any certaine compact or couenant: as the words here are,<note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                     <hi>lo teſimun, non imponetis ei:</hi> you ſhall not impoſe or lay vpon him vſury. It is not lawfull to couenant with a man certainely to pay ſo much; he may looſe by vſing the money, he may be in hazzard alſo of the principall; for the lender then to receiue a certaine gaine, where the borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is a certaine loſer were not iuſt.<note place="margin">What ſay you to theſe vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</note> Such indifferency muſt be vſed, as that the borrower be contented, as to be made pertaker of the gaine, that commeth by his money, ſo alſo proportionably to beare part of the loſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſecond Teſtimony, Dr. Smith.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Willet</hi> vpon Levit. p. 625.</note>THis is the full definition of vſury: <hi>Quando aliquis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit vſus rei gratiâ interpoſitâ pactione:</hi> When as any
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150798:27"/> things commeth for the vſe of money aboue the principall,<note place="margin">vſury defined.</note> by way of contract, or compact: for ſo it is ſayd in the law <hi>lo teſimun, non impones,</hi> Thou ſhalt not put vpon him vſury.</p>
                  <p>That opinion which condemneth all vſury,<note place="margin">vſury condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. 1 By Scripture.</note> is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon euident teſtimonies of Scripture, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.8. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.13.17. &amp; 22.12. and theſe places haue ſomewhat in them more generall, then to be reſtrained to the poore: as that in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.12. In thee haue they taken gifts to ſhed blood, in thee haue they taken vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and encreaſe, and thou haſt greedily gained of thy neighbour by extortion: theſe kinds of oppreſſion may be committed as well againſt the rich as poore, though more againſt theſe then the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Argument againſt vſury, is from the decrees, of counſels, and teſtimony of Fathers, which generally forbid all vſury. <hi>vide locum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is anſwered to theſe, and the like teſtimonies,<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                        <hi>Obiect.</hi> Idem p. 627.</note> that the Fathers ſpeake againſt cruell and vnconſcionable vſury: <hi>Quae omnibus ſeculis plus ſatis obtinuit,</hi> which preuailed too much in euery age.</p>
                  <p>But ſurely they condemne all vſury whatſoeuer:<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> in pſ. 36. con. 3.</note> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Si plus quam dedisti expectus accipere, fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratores:</hi> if thou exſpect to receiue more then thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, thou art an vſurer. And <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth, <hi>quid eſt vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra? venenum patrimonij: quid eſt vſura legalis? latro prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicens quid intendit,</hi> what is vſury? the poyſon of ones patrimony: what is legall vſury? a thiefe foreſhewing what he intendeth; <hi>inter praecept. familiar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>3</label> The third generall Argument againſt vſury is, from naturall reaſon: as <hi>Aristotle</hi> thus reaſoneth againſt it.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, from the vnprofitableneſſe of it:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Polit. 1. c. 9.</note> for he that is rich in money, may oftentimes want neceſſary food.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:150798:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ibid.</note>Secondly, from the infiniteneſſe of the deſire of money: all men that are deſirous of money, doe encreaſe it infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereas euery laudable act, hath a certaine and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate end.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, they peruert the end for the which money was appoynted, which was for commutation, and to be a meane to the end: but they make money it ſelfe the end.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the manner of the gaine ſheweth it to bee vnnaturall: for it is according to nature to reape profit from the fruits of the earth, or from Cattell: but it is againſt nature to reape gaine from men, from one another: and whenas money begetteth money; whereof vſury hath the name <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of begetting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiect.</note>To theſe reaſons ſome anſwer, That although money be barren of it ſelfe, yet by money one may purchaſe grounds which will bring him fruit:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> But ſtill the argument is good for originally this encreaſe commeth out of money by mans induſtry: and ſo by two things not apt to bring fruit, gaine is had: by men, and money: and beſides this anſwer ſerues not, but onely for profitable vſury: but where one taketh vp money to ſupply his want, and neceſſity, there ariſeth no ſuch fruit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The third Teſtimony, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Williams.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The true Church. p. 438.</note>THat you may perceiue and vnderſtand, how odious and how deteſtable this biting theft is, I beſeech you to conſider. Firſt, how vniuſt he is, eſpecially in theſe two things:<note place="margin">Vſurers vniuſt againſt all laws 1 Of nature:</note> 1 In ſelling that which he oweth vnto the poore, for the law of nature tels thee, that he which hath, ſhould lend and helpe him which hath not, as we ſee the floud, finding the emptineſſe of a poole, will not paſſe vntill it fils it;<note place="margin">2 Of Moſes. Luke 6.35. 3. Of grace.</note> the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> bids the ſame thing; and the law of grace confirmes it, ſaying, <hi>Doe good and lend ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for nothing againe:</hi> and yet the couetous man ſels that which God commands him to giue: and he lets that for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150798:28"/> vſe which the Lord inioyneth him to lend for loue.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 In eating that which he neuer laboured for;<note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> for the Lord ſayd, <hi>In the ſweat of thy face thou ſhalt eate thy Bread:</hi> but the Vſurer eateth the labour of other men,<note place="margin">The vſurer ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth what hee neuer labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for.</note> and for the vſe of his money he vſeth to get vineyards which hee planted not, Houſes that hee builded not, and many other things that he neuer laboured for.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, how cruell he is;<note place="margin">Hee is moſt cruell.</note> becauſe he eateth and drinketh that with ioy and laughter, which the poore man hath gotten with griefe and teares.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3 Hee is the worſt of all Theeues.</note> how for his theft hee tranſcends all other kind of Theeues whatſoeuer: for as there is not a more effectuall plague to hurt a man then a familiar enemy: ſo the Vſurers, being domeſticall foes, they doe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſh and diſinherit more men then any other Theeues can doe; becauſe other Theeues ſteale ſecretly and in the night time, but the Vſurers follow their trade manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though cunningly, day and night: and therefore, when the Romanes enioyned other Theeues to make double reſtitution for their theft, they compelled the Vſurers to reſtore fourefold for their tranſgreſſion.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</note> how fearefull is the puniſhment of ſuch theft; becauſe, as they haue ſpoiled others, ſo they ſhall be ſpoyled themſeues; and their ſpoyle will bee the greater: becauſe that as the Dog, ſnatching the Bread out of the Childrens hands,<note place="margin">1 In this world</note> ſnatcheth the hand withall; ſo Vſurers, ſeeking the wealth of the poore,<note place="margin">Idem p. 439.</note> are thereby become the vtter ruinne of the poore, and therefore their wealth ſhall be ſoone taken from them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 As they haue puniſhed the poore on Earth more then many others,<note place="margin">2 In Hell.</note> ſo their puniſhment in Hell ſhall be greater then moſt ſinners.</p>
                  <p>And in this there infernall puniſhment,<note place="margin">How the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and their children doe curſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly in hell</note> it is obſerued that the vſurers and their children ſhall perpetually curſe each other, the father ſaying, curſed art thou, O ſonne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that for thy ſake I am tormented in this flame; for I
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150798:29"/> became an vſurer, leſt I ſhould leaue thee a begger; I gathered wealth, that thou ſhouldeſt not be poore, and I was contented to be poore in grace, that thou mighteſt be rich in goods; and therefore I am now poore in all things, but in torments. And the ſonne, on the other ſide, ſaying vnto his father, nay, rather curſed art thou, O father, <hi>Quia niſi malè congregaſſes mihi diuitias, non malè congregatas conſeruaſſem;</hi> becauſe thou gathereſt thy wealth with iniquity, and lefteſt them vnto me with a curſe, which hath conſumed them and deſtroyed my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>That Seraphicall Doctor <hi>Antoninus,</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Florence,</hi> after he had heard the confeſſion of a wretched Vſurer,<note place="margin">The forme of an abſolution which Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vſed to an vſurer.</note> gaue him no other abſolution than, <hi>Deus miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur tui, ſi vult, et condonet tibi peccata tua, quod non credo: et perducat te in vitam aeternam, quod est impoſſibile:</hi> God be mercifull vnto thee, if he pleaſe, and forgiue thee thy ſinnes, which I doe not beleeue, and bring thee to eternall life, which is vnpoſſible: that is, <hi>Rebus ſic stantibus,</hi> if God doth not wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke a ſtrange conuerſion in his heart, and the Lord himſelfe threatneth, that he which robbeth or giueth to vſury, and receiueth the increaſe into his bags, he ſhall dye the death, and his blood ſhall be vpon him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The fourth Teſtimony, Dr. Sutton.</head>
                  <p>THere is no ſinne, be it neuer ſo prodigious and foule but his maſter hath ſome plea for it,<note place="margin">Lectures vpon Rom. 11. p. 296: vſurers excuſe their ſinnes. p. 476.</note> and ſome reaſon to vphold it. Some haue Scripture, as couetouſneſſe hath 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. Vſury hath, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.20. <hi>Vnto a stranger thou mayſt lend thy money vpon vſury, though not to thy brother.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Many perſwade themſelues that they haue lawfull callings when they haue none; ſuch as liue by vſury, carding, dicing, playing, theſe haue neyther the Author, God, nor the end, the common good.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:150798:29"/>
                  <p>No calling is lawfull,<note place="margin">Idem p. 477</note> when the action pleaſeth not God, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.<note place="margin">Vſurers haue no lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> By this I hope ſome will learne at laſt to giue ouer their calling, whereby they bring not honour, but diſhonour vnto God: thoſe that liue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vſury, by dicing-Houſes, by penning and acting of Playes, let them all remember this, mine heart trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to thinke, what calling theſe men haue, my Soule wonders how they glorifie God in them, I maruell how theſe make for a publicke good: How God is honoured, a kingdome bettered, the common good promoted by them I know not, I beleeue not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The fifth Teſtimony <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Wilkinſon.</head>
                  <p>LEt thoſe who plead this cauſe conſider,<note place="margin">Debt booke p. 61. 62. All vſury for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. Vſurers do not as they would be don vnto.</note> that God diſpenceth with no vſury, when <hi>Neſheh</hi> the bitting: and <hi>Tarbith,</hi> which they call the toothleſſe vſury are both condemned. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.8.13. That the lender, for eight or fiue in the hundred, deales not as he would be dealt withall, for he himſelfe would neyther giue eight, nor fiue, nor two, if hee could borrow freely; and the rule of loue is, to doe to all men as we would they ſhould do to vs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. Let them conſider how vſury is cried downe, among other oppreſſions <hi>Neh.</hi> 5. &amp; <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15.5. How it is condemned by the Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> in Clergy men, as a matter of filthy lucre, (if filthy lucre in Miniſters, then no righteous dealing in others.<note place="margin">Vſury the ruine of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands.</note>) how it hath beene the vtter ruine of many thouſands in our Nation; how in the Church of Rome at this day), all Vſurers are excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated monthly; how no man of note in all antiquity <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Manichees</hi> excepted) none I ſay of honeſty and learning,<note place="margin">No honeſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vſury for fifteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt.</note> for fifteene hundred yeeres after Chriſt hath euer vndertaken the defence thereof: wherefore as <hi>Ioaſh</hi> ſometimes ſayd to the men of <hi>Hophra,</hi> when they ſtood for <hi>Baal</hi> againſt <hi>Gideon,</hi> Will you contend for <hi>Baal?</hi> let him plead his owne cauſe: ſo ſay I to the patrons
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150798:30"/> of vſury; will you contend for Mammon? let him plead his owne cauſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſixt Teſtimony, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Smith.</head>
                  <p>VSury is vnlawfull, for:</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Vſury is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt charity. Sermon vſury.</note>Firſt, It is againſt the law of charity becauſe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, biddeth vs to giue euery man his owne, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no more then our owne: but vſury requireth more then her owne, and giues not to other their owne. Charity reioyceth to communicate her goods to other, and vſury reioyceth to gather other mens goods to her ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Againſt the law of nations.</note>Secondly, it is againſt the law of nations, for euery nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath ſome law againſt vſury, and ſome reſtraint againſt vſurers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Againſt the law of nature, and of God.</note>Thirdly, it is againſt the law of nature, that is the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall compaſſion which ſhould be among men: the rich ſhould diſtribute and doe good.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, it is againſt the Law of God. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. <hi>Leu.</hi> 25.36.<note place="margin">Gaine makes vſury lawfull.</note> 
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19.</p>
                  <p>Some thinke that vſury is lawfull, becauſe it is gainefull as <hi>Saul</hi> thought that the idolaters beaſts ſhould not be killed,<note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">☞</note> becauſe they were fat: But as he was commanded to kill the fat beaſts, as well as the leane, ſo we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to kill fat ſins, as well as leane ſins: gainefull ſins as well as prodigall ſinnes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>7.</hi> Teſtimony, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Wheatly.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Caueat for the couetous. p. 71. Vſury a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious iniuſtice. 3 ſorts of bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers.</note>VSury is a notorious iniuſtice: when a man makes a gaine of lending, and binds the party borrowing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration of his gaines or loſſes, to repay the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall with aduantage. For whereas there be three ſorts of men that vſe to borrow, either poore men, whom neceſſity driues to it, or vnthrifts, whom prodigality driues to it; or ſufficient men, that hope to make a commodity of it: it is apparent by the confeſſion euen of thoſe that would ſeeme to ſay ſomewhat for this vſury, (as if it were not a needy
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150798:30"/> ſinne ſimply that it is wicked to lend on Vſe to the poore needy borrower, for God hath ſtately commanded to lend vnto him freely. And for the vnthrift, it is alſo certaine that he ſhould not be lent to at all;<note place="margin">Vſurers gaine moſt by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts.</note> for that is to feede his iſſue with ill humors, and to put a Sword into his hand wherewith to deſtroy himſelfe: and thus the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers moſt accuſtomed and greateſt gaines are cut of. Now for the third kind of men, of them to exact gaine vnconditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally, not reſpecting their looſing or getting, is altogether againſt the Law of Charity, and equity both for the light of nature will not ſuffer any to deny this principle of Equity, that he which will haue part in wealth, muſt alſo haue part in woes; and he that will diuide the ſweet, muſt alſo diuide the ſower: he that will take of the good ſucceſſe, muſt alſo take of the bad. And the light of Religion will not ſuffer him that hath any of it, to deny this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Charity; that Chriſtians muſt ſerue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in loue, and not themſelues alone in ſelfe-loue: both which principles are directly contrary to the very trade of the Vſurer;<note place="margin">The Vſurer ſerues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone, not alſo his brother.</note> for he makes ſure for himſelfe to haue a part onely and infalliably in the profit, and therefore ſerues himſelfe alone, and not alſo his brother: and for this cauſe the Vſurer is ſet among thoſe that cannot come to dwell in the Mountaine of God: which hee ſhould not be, were he not vniuſt. So then the Vſurer, whether he do it plainely, or vnderhand, as men haue a thouſand policies to couer their ſinne in this reſpect, muſt vndergoe the imputation of liuing by wrong and iniurie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The eight Teſtimony M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Dod.</head>
                  <p>IN the ſame colourable theft is that common ſinne of Vſury, which is of euill report, and hurtfull effect amongſt men and is forbidden of God in the Law and Prophets. It is euident in <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25.35.36.<note place="margin">The cauſes of vſury. 1 Want of Gods feare.</note> That the feare of God, and a louing and mercifull regard of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150798:31"/> our brothers life,<note place="margin">2 Loue to our brethren.</note> be the preſeruatiues to keepe men from this Vſury: therefore the practiſe hereof doth grow from the want of the feare of God, and of compaſſion to our poore brother. Adde hereunto, that vſury is not a calling appointed of God, but a humane inuention, deuiſed by worldly men to gaine filthy lucre to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,<note place="margin">Vſury not a calling appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God.</note> whereby they liue of the ſweat of other mens brows, and doe many times adde affliction to the afflicted, and build vp themſelues in the ruines of their poore neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, whom they ought freely to ſupport.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ninth Teſtimony, Mr. Bolton.</head>
                  <p>OVt of the widenes of the conſciences of wicked men, proceed much mincing and excuſing, many interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,<note place="margin">Diſcourſe of true happines. p. 55. All vſury con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</note> fauourable conſtructions and diſtinctions of ſinne. As for example, that vſury is of two ſorts, biting and tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe; when all kind of vſury is peſtilent, and moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly damned in the booke of God.</p>
                  <p>Miniſters may tell the mercileſſe vſurer that he is infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly guilty of that ſinne,<note place="margin">Vſury condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the beſt Diuines. Idem p. 183.</note> of which a conuerted lew, an honeſt Heathen, a tolerable Turke, would be aſhamed and remorſefull: ſtigmatized by ioynt-conſent of charitable hearts, and ſtrongeſt current of beſt Diuinity, with a brand of extraordinary hatefulneſſe, hard-heartedneſſe and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty:<note place="margin">It is a fretting canker.</note> which at this day doth ſhrewdly ſhake the ſtrong ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news of this great Kingdome, like a fretting canker, with a plauſible inuiſible conſumption, doth daily waſte the ſtates,<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſucke the blood, and eate the liues of many poore diſtreſſed ones in this Land, fils townes and Cities with vnprofitable perſons, and the country with miſeries and inhumanities. Nay, and let carnall reaſon, couetous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, ſupercilious, obſtinate imperiouſneſſe fret, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict, rage, and reclaime as long as they will; to ſet aſide prouocation of Gods plagues, and conſideration of piety; euen in the ſenſe of nature, and morall conſcience, it caſts
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150798:31"/> an aſpertion of inexpiable ſhame and diſhonour vpon the ancient glory of this incomparable City.<note place="margin">vſurers bee Harpies and vultures.</note> It is very ſtrange that ſuch rauenous Harpies and vſurious Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (for ſo euen Paganiſme ſtiled them by the light of reaſon,) ſhould audaciouſly rouſt eſpecially on high, in the Eagles neſt, this Imperiall groue and Seat of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The tenth Teſtimony, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Adams.</head>
                  <p>THe Vſurer is a priuate theefe like <hi>Iudas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Adams workes p. 55. The vſurer like to Iudas.</note> and for the bag like <hi>Iudas,</hi> which he ſteales from Chriſt like <hi>Iudas,</hi> or rather from Chriſtians, that haue more need, and therefore worſe then <hi>Iudas.</hi> This is a man made out of waxe: His <hi>Pater noſter</hi> is a pawne: his Creed, is the condition of this obligation: his Religion is all religati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: a binding of others to himſelfe: of himſelfe to the Deuill,— infinite colours, mitigations,<note place="margin">Note.</note> euaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſtinctions are inuented, to countenance on earth, heauen-exploded vſury: God ſhall then fruſtrate all, when he powers his wrath on the naked conſcience. God ſayth, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take vſury.</hi> Goe now ſtudy pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, excuſes apolegies, diſpute the matter with God: hell fire ſhall decide the queſtion.</p>
                  <p>If Vſurers will not reſtore by themſelues,<note place="margin">Idem p. 120. vſurers ſhall reſtore by their poſterity</note> they ſhall by their poſterity. For as <hi>Pliny</hi> writes of the Wolfe, that it brings forth blind Whelpes: ſo the vſurer light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begets blind children, that cannot ſee to keepe what their fathers left. But when the father is gone to hell for gathering, the ſonne often followes for ſcattering. But God is iuſt. A good man leaueth his inheritance to his childrens children: and the wealth of the ſinner is laid vp for the iuſt.</p>
                  <p>An vſurer is knowne by his very lookes often,<note place="margin">Idem p. 454. The vſurer knowne by his lookes.</note> by his ſpeeches commonly, by his actions euer: he hath a leane cheeke, a meager body, as if he were fed at the Diuels
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150798:32"/> allowance: his eyes are almoſt ſunke to the backſide of his head with admiration of money. His eares are ſet to tell the clocke; his whole carcaſſe a meere Anatomy. Some Vſurers haue fatter carcaſſes, and can find in their hearts to lard their fleſh: but a common meagerneſſe is vpon all their conſciences. <hi>Foenus pecuniae, funus animae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nature hath ſet a pitch or terme in all inferiour things, when they ſhall ceaſe to increaſe. Old Cattell breed no longer: doted trees deny fruit; the tired earth becomes barren; onely the Vſurers money, the longer it breeds the luſtier;<note place="margin">Note.</note> and a hundred pounds put out twenty yeares ſince, is a grandmother of two or three hundred children; pretty ſtriplings, able to beget their mother againe in a ſhort time.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>EAch man to heauen his hands for bleſſing reares;</l>
                     <l>Onely the Vſurer needs not ſay his prayers.</l>
                     <l>Blow the Winde Eaſt or Weſt, plenty or dearth,</l>
                     <l>Sickneſſe or health, ſit on the face of Earth,</l>
                     <l>He cares not: Time will bring his money in:</l>
                     <l>Each day augments his treaſure and his ſin.</l>
                     <l>Be the day red or blacke in Calender,</l>
                     <l>Common, or holy, fits the Vſurer.</l>
                     <l>He ſtarues his Carcaſſe, and true money ſlaue,</l>
                     <l>Goes with full cheſts, and thin cheekes to his graue.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem p. 455.</note>The Vſurer ſhrinkes vp his guts with a ſtaruing dyet, as with knot-graſſe: and puts his ſtomacke into his purſe. He ſels time to his cuſtomers, his food to his cofers, his body to languiſhment, his ſoule to Satan.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The eleuenth Teſtimony, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Perkins.</head>
                  <p>VSury is a gaine exacted by couenant, aboue the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall,<note place="margin">vpon Com. 8. vſury defined.</note> onely in lieu, and recompence of the lending of it.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150798:32"/>
                  <p>vſury being conſidered as it is thus deſcribed, is quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Gods Word, and may very fitly be tearmed byting lucre. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22, 14.15. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.8. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The twelfth Teſtimony <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Fenton.</head>
                  <p>LEt euery one who deſireth to reſolue his conſcience for this matter by Scripture (the onely true ground of a Chriſtian reſolution I t him conſider, I ſay,<note place="margin">Treatiſe of vſury p. 48.</note> how ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vſury nor intereſt,<note place="margin">Vſury con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in Gods Booke.</note> biting vſury nor increaſe is euer once named in the Booke of God, but it is condemned; condemned amongſt ſuch abominations as bring a curſe in ſtead of a bleſſing: an eternall curſe vpon the Soule of the Vſurer, and a temporall curſe vpon his wealth and poſterity.</p>
                  <p>Let ſome of theſe tender conſciences,<note place="margin">Is it not a ſhame for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deny knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the Communion, and to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Vſurers.</note> who are ſo vrgent to call for warrant out of the booke of God, for euery ceremony and matter of forme in the Church, ſeeke a warrant for this their practice, which ſo neerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth them; and let them ſeeke it at the Oracle of God who hath not left it, as he hath many other things, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the diſcretion of the Church, or wiſdome of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, but hath vouchſafed to determine it in his owne booke to our hands: to ſet downe an expreſſe Law againſt it in <hi>Exodus:</hi> to renew and reuiue that Law againe and againe in <hi>Leuit.</hi> And <hi>Duter:</hi> to ratifie and confirme it with no other words then himſelfe vſed at the publiſhing of the whole Morrall Law; to ſpecifie the onely limitation which he meant to tolerate for a time; to adde the promiſe of bleſſing to the keepers of this Law: and to denuonce ſuch fearefull iudgements againſt the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the ſame: vpon their wealth and poſterity in this world, vpon their owne ſoules in the world to come.</p>
                  <p>The Vſurer hath great gaine and certaine:<note place="margin">Idem p. 101. Vſurers haue certaine gaine out of loſſe, &amp;c.</note> ſometimes out of little gaine: ſometimes out of no gaine: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of loſſe; alwayes out of vncertainties; alwayes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150798:33"/> out of labour and paines, out of care and coſt, out of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and perill to the borrower. Commeth all this on Gods Name?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Idem p 142, No writer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended vſury for fifteene hundred yeeres after Chriſt, Note.</note>There was neuer any Church or Churchman, carrying the name of a Chriſtian, who hath defended in writing any branch of vſury, for the ſpace of fifteene hundred yeares after Chriſt. Neyther was this for want of occaſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; for it hath beene both practiſed and written againſt in all ages. Neyther can we with modeſtie impute it to the ignorance of the Church: for as ſhee is acknowledged to be moſt Eagle-ſighted in the time of her purity; ſo when ſhe was ouerſhadowed with ſuperſtition, her wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in caſes of conſcience, for matters of morality were moſt exact: as by their ſchoole Diuinity is euident to be ſeene. Yet where ſhall we find any one, for ſo many ages of the Church, who could euer deuiſe a diſtinction to ſaue an vſurers ſoule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fentons</hi> Treatiſe of vſury ii able, to ſatisfie thoſe that be not deſperately minded.</note>He that deſires to be fully ſatisfied concerning the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſſe of vſury, by Scriptures, Fathers, the latter times of ignorance: by the teſtimonies of the Church aſſembled in Councels, by the teſtimony of Diuines in reformed Churches, by the teſtimonies of Philoſophers, Hiſtorians, by the three Lawes, 1 Canon, 2 Ciuill, 3 Common: by ſtrong and conuincing arguments: finally, he that deſires to haue thoſe motiues anſwered, which perſwade ſome to the lawfulneſſe of vſury, let him read with diligence the learned Treatiſe of vſury, written by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fenton,</hi> read his Treatiſe with a ſingle eye, iudge of what thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt without affection: and conforme thy affection to right iudgement.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The thirteenth Teſtimony M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Rogers, of Weathersfield.</head>
                  <p>THeſe being the moſt vſuall kinds of contracts, do ſhew the nature of the reſt,<note place="margin">7 Treatiſes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 8 Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. vſury vnlawfull</note> which are in vſe among men, and doe leaue no place to that oppreſſion in the world,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150798:33"/> called vſury, or any other ſuch ſeeking of mens priuate profit in their dealings, without regard of the common benefit of both: that is, when both parties are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for, to their contentation and ſatisfying according to equity, and to the meaning and prouiſion made by God in that behalfe: which is, that the one without the other ſhould not be benifited or inriched; but the one to haue care and conſideration of the other,<note place="margin">Regard had of both parties is no vſury.</note> and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of both (as I haue ſayd) reſpected which if it were regarded betwixt both parties, could in no wiſe be iuſtly complayned of: neyther is ſuch dealing of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and kind of vſury, whether it be in hiring and letting, or in any other kind of contract whatſoeuer; but that common dealing for 10 in the hundred, or 9, or 8, or any ſuch like, which is without due conſideration of the Common-wealth, and vpholding of both, is vtterly to be condemned.</p>
                  <p>Which if it be well and duely conſidered, will ſoone an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere all conſcionable men,<note place="margin">No vſe of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Church or Common-wealth.</note> about the queſtion of vſury and oppreſſion, that there can be no vſe of them in the Church of God, nor the Chriſtian Common-wealth: the Law-maker hauing ſayd of both, as of witchcraft and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, there ſhall be none ſuch in Iſrael, that is, among Gods people. And as for teaching others their duty, (eſpecially in money matters) who haue not giuen themſelues in full reſolution to be guided by Gods Word,<note place="margin">Why Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers prauaile not with vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</note> Preachers may ſooner weare their tongues to the ſtumpes, then they may preuaile with them.</p>
                  <p>If thou deſireſt the iudgement of other diuines, beſides theſe before mentioned; read, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bayne,</hi> his directions to a godly life, p. 172. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Philips,</hi> vpon <hi>Math.</hi> 4. p. 198. Mr. <hi>Dyke,</hi> vpon Repentance, p. 143, 144. Dr. <hi>Sclater,</hi> vpon the 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> p. 277. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Robrough,</hi> Balme from <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> p. 35, 176, 225, 285, 320, 325. 432. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Preſton,</hi> Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt couetouſneſſe, p. 33. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> Theologicall rules for the vnderſtanding of holy Scriptures, p. 70.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150798:34"/> and in his miſticall caſes and ſecrets of Diuinity, p. 180. Mr. <hi>Brinſley,</hi> in the third rule and watch of life, p. 97. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> of <hi>Dedham,</hi> Treatiſe of loue, p. 235, 236. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Web,</hi> on A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurs prayer, p. 323. 147. read alſo the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. part of the Homily, againſt the perill of Idolatry, p. 70. where vſury is ranked with groſſe ſins, and condemned for vniuſt gaine. Read the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. part of the Sermon or Homily for Rogation weeke, p. 225. where vſurers are ſaid to haue their goods of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, to be worſhipers of the diuell, to kneele downe to the diuell at his bidding. See alſo M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Scudder</hi> vpon the Lords Prayer, p, 276,</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Fenton,</hi> of vſury. p. 2. Vſurers not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perſwaded to leaue their ſinne.</note>It is now time to draw to the concluſion; it hath beene obſerued by wiſe men, that vſurers will not eaſily be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to forſake their ſinne; their gaine of Vſury is a ſweet gaine, without labour, without coſt, without perill; let it be granted that they will not forſake this ſo pleaſant, and ſo profitable a ſin; yet by theſe Teſtimonys, they may be conuinced in their iudgements, of the vnlawfulneſſe of vſury; and ſo they ſhall be made without excuſe at the laſt day, when Chriſt ſhall come in flaming fire with his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Angels to render vengeance to all diſobedient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
                  <p>As for you that make a trade of vſury if you ſhall thinke your iudgements to be of ſuch waight,<note place="margin">Idem p. 77. The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe reuerend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines ſhould make the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their trade.</note> that all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be not able to caſt the ſcale againſt you, yet I hope they will ſo much moue you, as to bring the ballance to a ſuſpence, that you will thinke vſury very queſtionable at the leaſt; and if it be queſtionable, then it is vnlawfull to be done. But if all theſe reuerend Biſhops and learned Diuines, will not ſo moue your vnderſtanding, to make it queſtionable; then I will ſay no more, and I can ſay no leſſe, but that you Vſurers thinke that you know ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.2.</note> And then S. <hi>Paul</hi> maketh vp the reſt, that you know nothing as yee ought to know it.</p>
                  <p>To him who knoweth vſury to be a ſinne, it is a ſinne, becauſe he knoweth it. To him that doubteth, it is likewiſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150798:34"/> a ſinne, becauſe he doubteth. And to the reſt it is a ſinne of ignorance, but of affected ignorance: whoſe eyes are blinded eyther with pride, becauſe they would be ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, or with lucre and gaine,<note place="margin">Vſury a ſinne of affected ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</note> becauſe they would not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe their conſciences by examining or diſcouering that ſinne wherein they haue ſo ſweetly ſlept, and doe ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues. But ſuch ignorance doth neyther excuſe nor extenuate the fault, but rather agrauate the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is wilfull.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Similitudes to which vſurers, and vſurie are reſembled.</head>
               <p>VSury is a thriuing occupation.<note place="margin">Vſury like the Perſian tree. Adams workes p. 503.</note> Vſury is like that Perſian tree, that at the ſame time buds, bloſſomes, and beares fruit. The moneys of intereſt are euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ſome ripe for the Trunke, others drawing to maturity, the reſt in the flowre approaching, all in the bud of hope. But the vſurer is mad; for his ſinne at once buds,<note place="margin">Vſurers mad.</note> bloſſomes, and brings forth the fruit of vengeance. Euery Bond he takes of others, enters him into a new obligation to Satan: as he hopes his debtors will keepe day with him, the diuell expects no leſſe of himſelfe. Euery forfeit he takes ſcores vp a new debt to Lucifer; and euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd land he ſeizeth on, enlargeth his dominion in hell.</p>
               <p>Money lent vpon vſury to a poore man to ſupply his need,<note place="margin">Vſury like new cloth vpon an old garment. Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> Pſ. 15. p. 206.</note> may not vnfitly be compared to a peece of new cloth ſowed vpon an old garment; for that, although it couer the rent for a time, and ſeemeth to haue mended the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet after a while, the new cloth fretteth the old, and bringeth away a part of it, and ſo maketh the rent much worſe.</p>
               <p>Though the vſurers ſometimes doe vaunt, how kindly they deale with their debtors,<note place="margin">Idem p. 254. Note.</note> in forbearing them from
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150798:35"/> yeere to yeere: yet the truth is, the longer they forbeare, the greater is their gaine, and though they deferre the borrowers miſery,<note place="margin">The Vſurer compared to the greedy Cat.</note> yet in deferring it, they do increaſe it: and therefore by ſome are not vnfitly compared to the greedy Cat, which though for a while ſhe plaieth with the ſilly Mouſe, yet in the end ſhe will bee ſure to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure it.</p>
               <p>The Vſurers money is like the biting of the Aſpe,<note place="margin">Vſurers money like the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Aſpe.</note> for euen as he which is bitten of the Aſpe, goeth to ſleepe, as if he were delighted, and through the pleaſantneſſe of his ſleepe dieth; ſo he which borroweth vpon vſury is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted for a time as one that had receiued a good turne; and ſo through the pleaſure of the imagined benefit hee doth not perceiue how he is taken captiue. For euen as the poyſon of the Aſpe,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Vſury diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth it ſelfe through all the borrowers goods.</p>
                     <p>It is like lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
                     <p>Apud Chriſoſt. 3. Homil 12. in fine.</p>
                     <p>Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> Pſ 15. p. 258. Vſurers drones <hi>Vſura est quaeſ: tuoſa ſegniti: es.</hi> Vſury is gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full idleneſſe.</p>
                  </note> ſecrety conueying it ſelfe into all the members, corrupteth the whole body: ſo vſury diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſing it ſelfe through all the borrowers goods, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerteth them into debt. And euen as leauen which is put into meale, infecteth the whole lumpe, and drawing it to it ſelfe, turneth it into the nature of leauen: ſo when vſury entreth into any mans Houſe, it draweth all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance vnto it, and turneth it into debt.</p>
               <p>The Philoſopher matcheth the Vſurer with the baud: and to the ſame purpoſe obſerue the coherence, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 23.18.19. It is a wonder therefore, that in the hiue as it were of the Common-wealth, ſuch drones are ſuffered, which liue of the ſweat, yea blood of other men: who out of other mens labour attaine eaſe, out of other mens hazard gaine ſecurity, out of other mens loſſe reape gaine.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Similes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LVther</hi> ſayth, an Vſurer is a blood-ſucker of the people:<note place="margin">In decalog.</note> and as a Worme in an Apple or Nut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth all that is within: ſo an Vſurer deuoureth the ſubſtance of the City by wonderfull and ſecrete meanes.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150798:35"/>
                  <p>The Vſurer,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Wilkinſon</hi> Debt booke p. 99.</note> whoſe trafficke and trade it is to make men miſerable, and to raiſe his gaine out of other mens aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, hee is ſaith <hi>Chryſostome, Quaſi manum ſuſcipiens et in naufragium impelleus.</hi> As a man taking one by the hand to pull out of the water, but kicking him backe againe to the Shipwracke of his ſubſtance, and of himſelfe, which is a rude and a barbarous part in any, to hurt infallibly,<note place="margin">The Vſurer hurts thoſe whom hee pretends to helpe.</note> whom hee pretends to helpe. This is one of the bitter Potions which the world reacheth forth to ouer pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers, and ouer-traders, which they are forced to drinke to the very dregges, when they cannot bee content to walke within their compaſſe.<note place="margin">Note.</note> As a man cannot touch Pitch but bee defiled therewith: ſo hee cannot deale with vſury without detriment, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> the firſt moment.</p>
                  <p>When the Vſurer ſaith that he lendeth for compaſſion,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Smith.</hi> 1 Sermon vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vſury. The Vſurer like the luye.</note> he meaneth for compaſſion of himſelfe, that hee may gaine by his pitty. The Vſurer loueth the borrower, as the Iuye loueth the Oke; the luye loueth the Oke to grow by it, ſo the Vſurer loueth the borrower, to grow rich by him. The Iuye claſpeth to the Oke like a louer, but it claſpeth out all the iuyce and ſap, that the Oke can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thriue after: So the vſurer lendeth like a friend, but he couenanteth like an enemy, for he claſpeth the borrower with ſuch bands, that euer after he diminiſheth, as faſt as the vſurer encreaſeth.</p>
                  <p>The Vſurer is like a Butlers box:<note place="margin">The Vſurer like a Butlers. box.</note> for as all the counters at laſt come to the Butler: ſo all the money at laſt commeth to the vſurer, ten after ten, and ten after ten, and ten to ten, till at laſt he receiue not onely ten for an hundred, but an hundred for ten. This is the only difference,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> that the Butler can receiue no more then he deliuereth: but the Vſurer receiueth more then he deliuereth.</p>
                  <p>He is like a Moath;<note place="margin">Like a Moath.</note> euen as a Moath eateth a hole in Cloth, ſo Vſury eateth a hole in ſiluer.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:150798:36"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Adams works p. 1058. Vſury a ſharpe thorne. Note.</note>The gentleſt vſury is a moſt ſharpe thorne, and pricks the ſides of the Country till the blood followes. An Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer with his money, is like a man that hath no worke of his owne, yet keepes a ſeruant to let out: and takes not onely hire of others for his daily labour, but chardg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to ſteale ſomewhat beſides, and neuer to returne home empty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">An vſurer worſe then all ſinners. Worſe then a Theefe. Then Hell.</note>An Vſurer is worſe then all ſinners, he is worſe then a Theefe: a Theefe robbeth but in the night, but the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer robbeth day and night.</p>
                  <p>He is worſe then Hell; for in Hell onely the wicked ſhall be puniſhed: but the Vſurer puniſheth; and ſpoileth both good and bad and ſpareth neyther holy nor vnholy.</p>
                  <p>He is worſe then a <hi>Iew,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Then a Iew.</note> for one <hi>Iew</hi> will not take vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of another: but the Vſurer will take vſury of his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian brethren.</p>
                  <p>He is worſe then death,<note place="margin">Then death.</note> for death killeth but the body, but the Vſurer killeth body and Soule.</p>
                  <p>He is worſe then <hi>Iudas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Worſe then Iudas.</note> for <hi>Iudas</hi> ſold Chriſt but once for thirty pence, but they ſell Chriſt continually, as often as they take vſury: <hi>Iudas</hi> reſtored the money againe, but the Vſurers neuer reſtore the money againe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Norrbbooke</hi> poore mans gardan f 270. Idem p. 2706. An Vſurer like a Pigge.</note> that they vniuſtly haue taken.</p>
                  <p>The Vſurer is like a Pigge, for while he liueth, he is good and profitable for nothing, for he will be euer root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp the Earth, running through, and tearing of hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: eating and deuouring vp good Corne, Beanes and Peaſon, ſo likewiſe doth the wicked ſwiniſh Vſurer whilſt hee liueth: but when the Pigge is dead, then there commeth profit by him to many: ſo the Vſurer, when death taketh him, then the poore may haue ſome profit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Vſurers like the Worme in timber. <hi>Powels</hi> poſits of vſury p 48.</note>The Worme <hi>Teredo</hi> is ſoft to touch, but it hath ſuch hard teeth, as it deuoureth and conſumeth the hard tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: So the Vſurer is a ſoft beaſt at the firſt to handle, but in continuance of time, the hardneſſe of his teeth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150798:36"/> will eat a man vp, fleſh and bone, if he haue not an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall regard to ſhune him.</p>
                  <p>The Vſurer is like the <hi>Beuer,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Vſurer is like the Beuer.</note> which biteth ſo ſore, as that he neuer looſeth his teeth, vntill he haue broken the bones. It may be truly ſayd of theſe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> deſolation and deſtruction is in their path: whereſoeuer they ſet foot, they make hauocke of all.</p>
                  <p>The Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> doth hedge in this ſinne betweene Bribery and Extortion. And in another place we ſhall finde,<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.12.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 22 25.</note> that it and oppreſſion is made both one: thus by Gods owne teſtimony theſe are oppreſſors.<note place="margin">The Vſurer compared to the neather milſtone. How he ſpends his time. Note.</note> Not vnaptly may we compare the vſurer to the neather milſtone, which is ſlow and ſturres not; he ſits at home, and ſpends his time in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilliſh Arithmeticke, in numeration of houres, dayes, and moneys, in Subſtraction from other mens eſtates, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of his owne, vntill he haue made diuiſion bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene his ſoule and Heauen, and diuided the earth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and himſelfe to hell. His Broker we may compare to the vpper milſtone (without which the neather milſtone may ſeeme vnprofitable) that is quicke &amp; ſtirring, &amp; runs round: the poore (like Corne) who betweene both theſe is grinded into powder.<note place="margin">Vſurers ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for our ſinnes.</note> Surely it is for our ſinnes that God ſuffers vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers amongſt vs: it may be he ſuffers theſe a while; as he did the <hi>Canaanites</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> leſt the wild beaſts ſhould breake in vpon them; leſt pride and a full eſtate ſhould ſpill mens ſoules. Yet we may ſafely ſay of theſe, as <hi>Ioſua</hi> did of thoſe, they are prickes in our ſides, and Thornes in our eyes. Now the mercy of God rid vs of them: let them bring what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, apologies, mitigations, euaſions, or diſtinctions they, poſſibly can inuent: let them reply, vſury is no ſinne, many learned men are of this opinion: yet what are they the better if,<note place="margin">Mr. Rogers Strange vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card p. 312. 313.</note> God himſelfe be not of the ſame mind thoſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men are of? and let them tel me if their conſciences can be ſo ſatiſfied. Would not the greateſt Vſurer willingly giue an hundred pound bag to be ſecured in this point? It is not ſafe wading farre in a queſtionable water.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:150798:37"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Perkins.</hi> vol. 3. p. 220.</note>The Vſurer may pretend he pleaſures the poore, but his helpe is no better then his is, that giues a draught of cold water to him, that is in a burning feauer, which ſeemes pleaſant at the firſt, but after turnes to his great an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Iewell.</hi> vpon Theſſ. p. 116. Idem p. 117.</note>Vſury in the middeſt of a Citty worketh ſuch good, as fire doth, when it is ſet to the roofe of a Houſe: or as the Plague doth when it is taken to the mideſt of the body and toucheth the heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">An Vſurer worſe then a Theefe.</note>An Vſurer is much worſe then a Theefe. For a Theefe is driuen by extremity and neede: The Vſurer is rich and hath no neede. The Theefe ſtealeth in corners, and in places where he may be vnknowne: the Vſurer openly and boldly, at all times, and in any place. The Theefe, to releeve his Wife and Children: the Vſurer to ſpoyle his neighbour,<note place="margin">The Vſurer a Theefe at all times.</note> and to vndoe his Wife and Children. The Theefe ſtealeth from the rich, which haue enough: the Vſurer from the poore that hath nothing. The Theefe ſleeth, and will be ſeene no more: the Vſurer ſtandeth by it, continueth, &amp; ſtealeth ſtill: day and night, ſleeping and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,<note place="margin">Note.</note> he alwayes ſtealeth. The theef repenteth of his deed, he knoweth he hath done wrong and is ſorry for it: the Vſurer, thinketh it is his owne, that is well gotten, and neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth,<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> vpon Vſury p 95.</note> but defendeth, and maintaineth his ſinne impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently. The Theefe, if he eſcape, many times becommeth profitable to his countrey, and beſtoweth himſelfe paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in ſome trade of life: the Vſurer leaueth his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, forſaketh his husbandry, giueth himſelfe to nothing, whereby his countrey may haue benefite. The Theefe is ſatisfied at length:<note place="margin">The Vſurer ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſatisfied.</note> the Vſurer hath neuer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, the belly of the wicked will neuer be filled: as the Sea is neuer filled with water, though all the ſtreames of the world runne into it: So the greedineſſe of an Vſurer is neuer ſatisfied, though he gaine neuer ſo vnreaſonably. The Sea is profitable: the Vſurer is hurtfull and dangerous. By the Sea we may paſſe and come ſafely to the Hauen:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150798:37"/> but no man paſſeth by vſury without loſſe or Shipwracke.</p>
                  <p>Vſurers are in worſe caſe, then common ſtrumpets,<note place="margin">Vſurers in worſe caſe then harlots. Dr. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> of vſury, p. 138</note> or harlots be; for a drab is not bound to make reſtitution of that ſhe hath gotten vnlawfully, by abuſing her body in filthyneſſe, but onely to doe penance: and yet an vſurer muſt reſtore his euill gotten goods, becauſe he hath ſtolne them, or elſe, he cannot be receiued into the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tully,</hi> in his firſt booke of Offices, compareth vſurers to vile artificers, that get their wealth by lying deadly,<note place="margin">Idem p. 147.</note> and vttering falſehood to ſaue themſelues from famine. And with the vſurers, he reckoneth tole-takers, cuſtomers, and ſuch money Officers, that pille and polle both Prince and people. <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſayth, that vſurers and bauds may well goe together, for they gaine by filthy meanes all that they get.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6. An anſwer to all ſuch Arguments as perſwade ſome <hi>to the lawfulneſſe of vſury.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>1 Argument,</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>from the Parable,</hi> Math. <hi>25.27.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Thou oughteſt therefore to haue put my money to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changers, and then at my comming I ſhould haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued mine owne with vſury.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>1 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sclater</hi> vpon 1 Theſ. 5 p. 392. 393.</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>IS it not a worthy argument for vſurious contracts: drawne from the parable? worldlings looke for their owne with vſury; ſo the Lord for aduantage of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by his gifts. Approues he their practiſe? or rather vpbrayds our negligence, by compariſon drawne from mens courſes in euill? They were beſt ſay, they may imbeazle their maſters goods, becauſe Chriſt,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150798:38"/> by that worldlings wiſedome, would teach vs prouidence for our ſoules: or becauſe he reſembles his comming to a Thiefe in the poynt of ſuddenneſſe, thence inferre the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of theeuery. Compariſons are borrowed from things ſinfull,<note place="margin">Compariſons why borrowed from things ſinfull.</note> and vnlawfull, to teach truth, and admoniſh of duety: the vſe of them is, not to iuſtifie their euill, but to remember vs of duety, or to explaine his truth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>2 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Similitudes and Parables vſed in Scripture doe not hold in euery thing but wherein they are compared.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Smith,</hi> in <hi>Wilet</hi> vpon Leuit. p. 627. 1 Theſ. 5.2. Reuel. 5.5. 1 Pet. 5.8.</note> As Chriſt, for his ſudden comming, is likened to a thiefe in the night, yet hereby is not theft iuſtified: and as Chriſt is reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to a Lyon for ſtrength and courage, ſo the diuell for cruelty; and ſo here, the ſpirituall increaſe of Gods gifts is likened to vſury, for the thing, that is, the encreaſing, not to iuſtifie the manner. 2. And further, here the word vſury, <hi>Metaphoricè accipitur pro ſuper excreſcentia bonorum ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alium:</hi> is metaphorically taken for the encreaſe of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graces, <hi>Aquin.</hi> And ſo ſpiritually, the Lord receiueth vſury from vs in the encreaſe of his gifts,<note place="margin">in Pſal. 36. Con. 3. Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſury.</note> and we vſury from him, as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Si vis foenerare, foenera deo, foene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator minus vult dare, et plus accipere: hoc fac et tu, da mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica, accipe magna, da temporalia, accipe aeterna,</hi> if thou wilt be an vſurer, put out to vſury to God: an vſurer will giue leſſe, and take more, doe thou ſo, giue ſmall things, and take great, giue temporall things, and receiue eternall.</p>
                     <p>If theſe anſwers will not giue thee ſatisfaction, as what will ſatisfie a reſolued vſurer, whom the god of this world hath blinded? then conſult with other Diuines of ſound learning and ſincere iudgment, as: with M. <hi>Fentons</hi> Treatiſe vpon vſury, p. 14. p. 137. M. <hi>Dyke,</hi> of the deceitfulneſſe of mans heart, p. 209. Bb, <hi>Downam,</hi> vpon Pſ. 15. p. 285. Bb, <hi>Iewel,</hi> vpon 1 Theſ. p. 140.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:150798:38"/>
                  <head>2 Argument, for the lawfulneſſe of vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>I would willingly pay ten in the hundred, if I had need, and therefore I may take ſo.<note place="margin">I. M.</note>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. THat royall rule, Doe as thou wouldſt be done by,<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Boltons</hi> directions for a comfortable walking with God. p. 208. 209. <hi>Fenton</hi> of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury. p. 137, 138. Dr. <hi>Pye,</hi> of vſury, p. 9. Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> Pſ. 15. p. 233. 234. <hi>Powels</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of vſury p. 90.</note> muſt be vnderſtood and expounded, according to to the grounds of a good conſcience, dictates of right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and directions of a iuſt and rectified will: not out of the miſts and miſeries of a depraued and exorbitant iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Otherwiſe <hi>Abimelech, Saul,</hi> and other of that deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ranke and reſolution, might conclude, that it were lawfull for them to kill other men, becauſe they were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be killed themſelues, See <hi>Iudg,</hi> 9.54. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.4. for they might ſay, they did but as as they would be done by. It would alſo follow very abſurdly: the Magiſtrate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the malefactors caſe would gladly be pardoned, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt pardon the malefactor: ſome ſonne of <hi>Belial</hi> would be content villanouſly to proſtitute his wife whom he cares not for himſelfe, to others; therefore he may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe another mans wife whom he loues better: theſe, and the like abominable and abſurd conſequents, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the vanity of the vſurers inference, and that Chriſts rule is not ſo generall, but reſtraineable to that will, which is orderly,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and honeſtly guided by the light of nature, and Gods Law.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We muſt then haue recourſe to this generall foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the ſecond table,<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Taylors</hi> Circumſpect walking, p. 163. 164.</note> and fetch light and direction thence: when we haue no expreſſe and ſpeciall word in Gods Booke; but the Scriptures haue clearely and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined and reſolued the poynt of vſury.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 If the vſurer were in the borrowers caſe, he would not willingly, as he pretends, giue ten in the hundred. I meane with an abſolute and free will, but of force and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, becauſe without paying after that rate,<note place="margin">Note.</note> he could not
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150798:39"/> haue it. If a man would borrow vpon Vſury, to buy land, ingroſſe, foreſtall, or compaſſe ſome vnlawfull matter; that were a corrupt will, and no rule: but if his deſire ſo to borrow were iuſt and lawfull, as in ſome caſes it may be, then it is no intire will, but mixed and forced by ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, for the auoyding of a greater euill: and therefore denyed in the eye both of law and reaſon, to be any will at all.<note place="margin">Note:</note> He that would borrow, ſhould haue need to borrow, for a needleſſe deſire is vnlawfull, and an ingenious man who hath need to borrow, would not willingly borrow but for need, much leſſe would he pay vſury. Therefore the will of the borrower, in this caſe, is eyther corrupt, or no will at all, and ſo conſequently without the compaſſe of Chriſts rule.</p>
                     <p>The will of the borrower in this caſe, is like the will of an honeſt traueller,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> in giuing his pur e to an arrand thiefe: for the feare he ſhould looſe both purſe and life. Is ſuch a man willing, thinke you to looſe his money? or like the will of a man, whoſe houſe being on fire, pluckes downe part thereof to ſaue the reſt: willingly indeed as the caſe ſtands with him,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> yet not ſimply, but vpon neceſſity. So the borrowers will is not free, but forced, and ſo a will againſt a will.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>3 Argument.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Some Diuines haue vndertaken the defence of ſome kind of vſury, eſpecially to the rich, and ſo haue animated ſome in that courſe.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>1 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Taylers</hi> Progreſſe of Saints p. 96.</note>This Doctrine brought to his tryall will not hold, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is ſuch a conſumer of mens eſtates, and ſo vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as the Lord would not admit of it in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his enemies whom he would haue quite conſumed. Beſides, men deceiue themſelues in their diſtinction: for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150798:39"/> God in the caſe of vſury diſtinguiſheth not betweene the rich and poore of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but betweene the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> and the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> betweene ſtrangers and brethren. The poore indeed are mentioned,<note place="margin">The poore why mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> but onely thus: 1. Becauſe they haue moſt neede to borrow 2. Becauſe they are moſt liable to wrong and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. 3. The Commandement of loane is made eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their good. 4. Vſury on them is a more grieuous ſin and crying, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.21.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ob.</hi> But if it were vnlawfull, God would forbid it to the ſtranger. <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. The Morrall Law forbids it to all. 2. It is by God diſpenſed with, by a iudiciall, for the hardneſſe of the hearts of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> for the vniuſtice of the Gentiles, who exacted it on the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and for the ouerthrow of the <hi>Canaanits.</hi> The word is <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.20. Not <hi>Lemicro</hi> but <hi>Lamicro, Extraneo huic,</hi> that is, to this ſtranger, meaning the <hi>Canaanite.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">See <hi>Fenton.</hi> of vſury p. 46.</note> It is no more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full then Poligamy or a Bill of diuorce, which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Inſtitutor. 4. When the <hi>Canaanites</hi> were deſtroyed, all vſury was afterward abſolutely forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15. And <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.8. <hi>Hier</hi> on <hi>Leu.</hi> 18. In the Law Vſury is forbidden onely to brethren, but in the Prophets to all abſolutely: and in the Goſpell much, more, becauſe all are now brethren.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>2 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If any learned men do allow that vſury, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, and practiſed in the world,<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> on Pſ. 15. p. 310.</note> I oppoſe to them the iudgements of many more worthy and learned men in this Age, the teſtimonies of all the learned in former ages, both Chriſtians and heathen, the cenſures of Councels, the authority of the Word of GOD.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>3 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>If thoſe Diuines that ſpeake or write for vſury proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called, be Vſurers themſelues;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sclater:</hi> vpon Romane p 122.</note> may not this ſinne winde it ſelfe into their affections, and thence creepe into
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150798:40"/> their iudgements, and vnderſtandings, till it haue eaten out all ſoundnes of iudging and diſcerning betwixt good and euill? Doth not adultery creepe from the body to the affections bewitching them? Doth it not blind the iudgement: to thinke and cenſure it but a tricke of youth? Drunkenneſſe what an inward thirſt of the deſire workes it? And how eaſily inclines it to iudge it no worſe then good-fellowſhip, yea ſo good as a poynt of manhood.</p>
                     <p>This aduantage hath the diuell gotten againſt vs in the practiſe of this ſinne,<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                           <hi>Fenton</hi> of vſury p. 3. Vſury why a bewitching ſinne.</note> that vſury being a trade ſo gainefull in reſpect of others, ſo eaſie, ſo cheape, ſo ſecure without all labour, coſt, or perill, being alſo ſo common, behouefull, and requiſit in theſe times for all occaſions; it hath bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched euen the conſciences of thoſe who are moſt tender in other matters. For if the heart and affection be once won and poſſeſſed, it is an eaſie matter euen by ſlight proofes to turne the braine. <hi>Quod nimis miſeri volunt, hoc facilè cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> ſtrong affection giueth great credit to weake argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: whereas indeed it ought to be contrariwiſe; that our naturall proneneſſe, and the generall inclination of the world to this practiſe of vſury, ſhould moue a well tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red iudgement the rather to ſuſpect the lawfulneſſe of it, and the ſoundneſſe of ſuch reaſons, as are brought for it. <hi>Perit omne iudicium, cum res tranſit ad affectum.</hi> Men loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by affection looke through a miſt or a painted glaſſe; to whom nothing appeareth in his natiue colour and due proportion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>3 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Powels</hi> poſit. of vſury, p. 52, 53.</note>Neuer any Diuine, that euer I could ſee or heare of, euer allowed vſury, but with ſuch caueats and leſſons, as alter the quality of vſury, and make it indeed no vſury at all.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Caluin</hi> in Ezek. 18. <hi>Wilet</hi> vpon Exod. p. 511.</note>1 All Diuines condemne it, as when men make a trade of it. <hi>Quiſquis ex profeſſo foeneratur, ille omnino debet ab ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum conſortio reijci.</hi> Thus alſo Dr. <hi>Willet,</hi> he that lendeth his money vpon vſury (ſayth he) muſt not be ſuch a one as maketh it his trade to liue by letting of money. And of all
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150798:40"/> other trades to be a profeſſed vſurer is moſt odious.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 They abſolutely condemne vſury of vſury.<note place="margin">Iun. in <hi>Leuit</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Vſura vſurarum, iudicio bonorum omnium etiam apud infideles dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata ſemper et infamis fuit.</hi> Yet this in it ſelfe is no more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull then vſury.</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Cautions to be obſerued by Vſurers, and that <hi>Exactè,</hi> to be preciſely kept, as <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Caluin</hi> ſayth.</head>
                        <item>1 <hi>Ne exigatur ab egente:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">See <hi>Fenton</hi> of vſury p. 62. 63. <hi>Ameſins de conſcientia.</hi> cap. 44. quae. 4, <hi>Perkins</hi> Condit. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, 8: <hi>Tantundem aut plus,</hi> Caluin. Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> in Pſ. 15. p 274 275.</note> it muſt not be taken of the needy, or ſuch as be vrged to borrow vpon neceſſity.</item>
                        <item>2 The vſurer muſt not be ſo addicted to gaine, but that he muſt be ſtill ready furniſhed, and willing to furniſh his poore neyghbour in his need, freely.</item>
                        <item>3 The rule of Chriſt muſt euer be his touchſtone, to deale no otherwiſe then he would be dealt, with in the like caſe.</item>
                        <item>4 The borrowers gaine muſt be ſo much more at the leaſt as the vſurers intereſt comes vnto.</item>
                        <item>5 That not onely a reſpect be had to the borrower but to the good of the Common-wealth alſo, that, that receiue no preiudice:</item>
                        <item>6 That the vſurer neuer exceed the ſtint ſet downe in the Country, or Common-wealth where he liues.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>And becauſe <hi>Zanchie,</hi> who is held another great patron of vſurers, doth vndertake to ſet downe the true meaning of <hi>Caluin, Bucer,</hi> and others in fauour of vſury, let vs heare what vſury that is, which they meant.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lictat paciſci de lucro, ſed adhibitâ ſemper conditione vel expreſſâ vel tacitâ, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> in mente pij creditoris confirmata: nempe, vt ſi certò compereris, cui tuam dediſti pecuniam, cum vel parum, vel nihil lucri feciſſe, id<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> non ſuâ culpa aut neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentiâ, ſed propter res aduerſus, et quia dominus noluit eius laboribus benedicere: tu quo<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> vel nihil, vel minus quàm erat in pactis accipias. Imo hoc animo eſſe debes, ô creditor, vt ſi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitor, non ſolum non fecit lucrum, ſed etiam accepit damnum,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150798:41"/> tu quoque damni aliquid cum illo patiaris: hoc enim poſtulat aequitas et charitas.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Vſury that <hi>Zanchie</hi> allowes,</note>It is lawfull to couenant for lucre, but vnder a condition either expreſſed in the couenant, or kept in mind, that if it appeare the borrower ſhall gaine little or nothing, (if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his owne default he proues a looſer:) thy vſury ſhall be little or nothing: and further if he loſe of the principall, thou muſt beare part of the loſſe. For equity and charity require this. This is the vſury which <hi>Zanchie</hi> defendeth, and this (ſayth he) was the meaning of <hi>Bucer</hi> and the reſt.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zanchie</hi> in Epiſt. ad Eph. 4. quaeſt. 4 p. 173.</note> Yet this is nothing but meere partnerſhip. If the lender take part of loſſe as well as of gaine, it is no vſury.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>4 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>The Law allowes eight in the hundred, therefore it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dyke,</hi> deceitfulneſſe of the heart, p 205.</note>THus the common vſurer deceiueth himſelfe; why the Law allowes eight in the hundred: yea, but the law onely ſtints, and limits it to eight in the hundred, and ſo farre giues way to it for the preuenting of a greater miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. And this will not be enough to excuſe the vſurer in the <hi>Court of Conſcience:</hi> thus the Iewes deceiued themſelues in the matter of their Poligamy, in hauing many wiues; and in their diuorces for euery trifle;<note place="margin">Math. 19.8.</note> they thought <hi>Moſes</hi> Law had allowed them in theſe ſinnes: whereas our Sauiour ſheweth, <hi>Moſes</hi> onely gaue a toleration for the hardnes of their hearts.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> in Pſ. 15. p. 265</note>The permitting of vſury, argues that vſury in it ſelfe is euill, and the rule of conſcience muſt be fetched, not from the ciuill lawes of men, but from the Word of God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Smith.</hi>
                        </note>The vſurer herein is like the Iewes, who ſayd, <hi>We haue a</hi>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:150798:41"/> Law, and by our Law he ought to die, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 19.7. when they could not ſay, by Gods Law, he ought to die: they ſayd by our Law he ought to die: ſo when the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer cannot ſay, by Gods Law I may take vſury; he ſayth, by mans Law I may take vſury: this is the pooreſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of all the reſt: for if Gods Law forbid thee, can any Law of man excuſe thee?</p>
                     <p>In that act of Parliament wherein vſury was ſtinted at eight in the hundred, and at the latter end of that act,<note place="margin">Anno Viceſimo primo Iacobi. regis.</note> it is prouided: that no words in that Law contained, ſhould be conſtrued, or expounded, to allow the practiſe of vſury, in point of Religion or conſcience.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <head>5 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Vſury is not forbidden in the new Teſtament, therefore it is lawfull.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>I Deny this conſequence:<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Pie.</hi> Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Spright coniured p. 81 82, 83. Note. Many groſſe ſinnes not for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bidden by name in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> there is no ſpeciall mention of the forbidding of it by name in the new Teſtament: <hi>Ergo</hi> it is lawfull. For there are many breaches of the Morrall Law, yea many groſſe ſinnes, which are not expreſſely mentioned, and forbidden by name in the new Teſtament: as namely profaning of the Sabbath day: all the degrees of inceſt ſaue one; remouing the neighbours marke: taking for pledge, or vpon execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a poore mans onely weed; remouing of Landmarks, Polygamy; ielouſie, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 An argument drawne from the teſtimony of ſome one part of the Scripture negatiuely, doth not hold, it is ſufficient that it is forbidden in the old Teſtament, and namely in the Mortall Law of God, which is common and perpetuall; and farre bee it from vs to thinke that Chriſt in his Goſpell alloweth any ſin which is fordidden in the Morall Law.</p>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150798:42"/>
                     <p n="3">3 Neyther is the taking of vſury of a poore man, that is in neuer ſo great diſtreſſe, forbidden by name in the new Teſtament, and therefore by this argument it ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo lawfull.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 By conſequence vſury is ſufficiently forbidden in the new Teſtament, as ſometimes vnder the contrary affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue: for where free lending is commanded, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.42.<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> Pſ. 15 p. 282. 283.</note> Not free lending (that is vſury) is condemned: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnder the generall, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.6. Sometimes abſtinence from vſury is commanded vnder the arguments of the greater and leſſe, as <hi>Luke.</hi> 6.35. Sometimes by an argument drawne from the leſſe, euen ſinners, ſayth our Sauiour, are willing and ready to lend one to another without vſury, how much more doth it become you that are Chriſtians; to lend one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without vſury?</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>6 Argument for Vſury.</hi> 
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>It was in the Apoſtles time, therefore had it beene a ſinne they would haue condemned it</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> Pſ. 15. p. 284.</note>I greatly doubt of this aſſertion, that vſury was in the time of Chriſt and his Apoſtles commonly practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Romanes: ſeeing <hi>Tiberius</hi> in the latter part of his reigne had vſed effectuall meanes for the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vſury, as <hi>Alexander</hi> ab <hi>Alexandro</hi> reporteth: but much more in reſpect of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> among whom the practice of vſury was forbidden by the Law of God, and to whom our Sauiour giueth this teſtimony, that the very ſinners among them would lend one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to receiue as much as they lent.<note place="margin">Luke 6.34. Iames 5.3.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
                        <hi>Iames</hi> alſo find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth fault with the rich men of that time,<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Pie.</hi> of vſury p. 84. 85.</note> that they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered their gold and ſiluer to ruſt, which they would not haue done if they had beene addicted to vſury: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:150798:42"/> the leſſe practiſe of vſury in thoſe times, may be ſome reaſon why it is not expreſſely mentioned in the writings of the Apoſtles.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="argument">
                  <head>7 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>The law which forbiddeth vſury, is not morall, but iudiciall, and therefore not belonging to vs: they proue it to be a law iudiciall, becauſe vſury is permitted towards a ſtranger.<note place="margin">Deut. 23.20.</note>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>1 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1 If it were a iudiciall law, yet the equity thereof,<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> Pſ. 15. p. 207.</note> which is perpetuall, would appertaine to vs, <hi>viz.</hi> that vſury is not to be impoſed vpon a brother: but behold we Chriſtians are all brethren in Chriſt, this difference of Iew and Gentile being taken away,</p>
                     <p n="2">2 The law which commandeth free lending, is not iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall but morall, and is therefore renewed by our Sauiour Chriſt, therefore the law which forbiddeth vſury or lending for gaine, is morall; for the ſame law which commandeth the affirmatiue, condemneth the negatiue.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Vſury is reckoned in the Scripture among the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of the morall law.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Fenton</hi> of vſury, p. 45.</note> Looke into the Prophets and they euer combine this ſinne of vſury with the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the morall law in the higheſt degree, with lying, back-biting, deceit, wrong, bribery, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15. with idolatry, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, adultery, cruelty, vnmercifulneſſe to the poore, bloodſhed, and murder, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. with the profanation of holy things: with the abomination of vncleaneneſſe: with the vnnaturall ſinnes of inceſt, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> Vſury (ſayth S. <hi>Baſil</hi>) is placed among the greateſt abominations; all of them tranſgreſſions of the morall law.</p>
                     <p>It is true indeed, there is a iudiciall and politique to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration annexed vnto this law, that the Iewes might take
<pb facs="tcp:150798:43"/> vſury of ſtrangers:<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.20.</note> but that maketh not the law it ſelfe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall but rather morall. The Iewes had a diuorce per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them in the ſame booke of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the next chapter, and yet the 7 Commandement, to which that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth, is morall notwithſtanding; in like manner the Iewes might take vſury of ſtrangers,<note place="margin">chap. 24.1.</note> which was a peculiar toleration for that nation, yet the law againſt vſury is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="argument">
                  <head>8 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>If vſury be not lawfull for any to practiſe alas what ſhall become of thoſe Orphans and widowes in theſe vniuſt daies, which haue ſtockes of money left vnto them, and want skill to employ the ſame.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Fenton</hi> of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury. p. 115,</note>VVHat ſhall become of them? by the helpe of God they may doe well. My greater care is, what ſhall become of thoſe Orphanes and Widowes in theſe vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table daies, which haue no ſtockes at all left vnto them. Though I confeſſe both the one and the other are alike in this, that they be not ſo able to helpe themſelues as others be. Therefore there be no two eſtates among men, ouer whom God hath a more prouident and tender care, then ouer<note n="(a)" place="margin">Deut. 10.18. &amp; 14.29. &amp; 18.11, 14. &amp; 24 17 20. Pſ. 68.5. Pſ. 146.9.</note> widowes and fatherleſſe children.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Exod. 22.22, 23, 24.</note>Hath God then ſo many waies bound himſelfe by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to prouide for Widowes and Orphanes, and ſhall theſe by vſury withdraw themſelues out of his fatherly protection? ſhall theſe be ſecured by vſurious contracts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the act of God himſelfe? verily God will take it more vnkindly at their hands, then at any other.</p>
                     <p>If Almighty God in wiſedome had thought it meet to haue tolerated vſury in theſe perſons, he might as eaſily haue mentioned the ſame, as he doth the toleration of len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſtrangers. But it was ſo farre from Gods meaning, that in the very ſame place, where he maketh a law for the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150798:43"/> ſafegard of Orphans and Widowes,<note place="margin">Exod 22.22.23 24.25.</note> preſently and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly vpon it, is annexed the Law againſt vſury. Shall then theſe who are ſo well prouided for, by a ſpeciall Law of God, be tranſgreſſors of the very next Law vnto it? God forbid.</p>
                     <p>Let Widowes and Orphans, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam.</hi> in Pſ. 15. p. 268. <hi>Dod.</hi> in Com. 316. Dr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vpon vſury p. 70.</note> Eyther imploy their goods in ſome honeſt trade, wherein they haue as good cauſe to expect a bleſſing from God, as any other: or let them deale by partnerſhip; or if other meanes faile, let annuities be bought for their liues, or Lands, or Rents purchaſed for euer; or let ſome other honeſt courſe be taken, which wiſe men can eaſily deuiſe, if they liſt: how Orphans may be maintained without impairing of their ſtocke.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="argument">
                  <head>9 Argument for Vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>The ſtate of the City cannot ſtand: trafficke cannot bee maintained: tradeſmen cannot liue without Vſury: therefore vſury is lawfull.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. I demaund firſt of theſe Tradeſ-Men,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Fenton</hi> of vſury p. 121.</note> who cannot liue in their trade without taking vp at intereſt: is their meaning that they cannot liue in that faſhion as they doe, maintaine their wiues in thoſe faſhons that they do: driue their trades to that height which they doe? If this be the caſe, the anſwer is eaſy:<note place="margin">Prou. 5.15.</note> it may be God would not haue them carry ſo great a ſaile as they doe, but to drinke of the waters of their owne well,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and content themſelues with ſuch meanes as Gods fatherly prouidence doth offer them:<note place="margin">Prou. 15.16.</note> there is no neceſſity for a man to inrich him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by ſuch practiſes, as be eyther forbidden or doubtfull. <hi>Better is a little with the feare of the Lord, then great treaſure with trouble;</hi> trouble of conſcience at the houre of death. Thus farre we do agree: whoſouer layeth this for his ground that he will be rich,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9.</note> muſt inſnare his conſcience with many
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150798:44"/> neceſſary euils, whereof vſury is one: neceſſary, I ſay, not to a religious honeſt man, who is content with his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; but to him who reſolueth he will be rich: for they that will be rich (ſaith the Apoſtle) fall into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and ſnares,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9.</note> which drowne men in perdition and deſtruction.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 If it be propounded, that trade and commerce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and man cannot be maintained in this City without borrowing and lending:<note place="margin">Luke 6.13. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> that is alſo granted. Gods Law did euer intend that men ſhould lend one to another; in charity to the poore: in friendſhip to their equalls, to receiue the like courteſie againe. Which duty if men would performe, three were no neceſſity of vſury.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The third point then followeth. Preſuppoſing the cuſtome and corruption of theſe times wherein men will not lend freely as they ought; is there not a neceſſity of vſury admit that be granted: who did impoſe this neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?<note place="margin">Note.</note> if God; then is this reaſon good, vſury is neceſſary, therefore lawfull. But if men or eſtates haue drawne a neceſſity of ſinning vpon themſelues by the cuſtome of ſinne, doth this extenuate or aggrauate the fault? Woe be vnto them (ſayth the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi>) who draw ſin,<note place="margin">Eſay 5.18.</note> as with cart-Ropes. Cities and Incorporations haue drawne a neceſſity of this ſinne vpon themſelues by three ſtrong cart-Ropes of iniquity.<note place="margin">3 Cauſe of the neceſſity of vſury.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt the hardneſſe of mens hearts, and want of charity in thoſe who be well able to lend and will not, haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced many to pay vſury.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, the couetous deſire and pride of borrowers, who out of an inſatiable appetite to compaſſe great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, do take vp great ſummes of money, for money: that no money is to be ſpared for ſuch as be true bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers indeede.<note place="margin">Iſ. 5.8.</note> 
                        <hi>Woe vnto them that ioyne, Land to Land till there be no place for the poore to dwell in.</hi> That is the Country woe. But vpon the ſame ground, it is inferred: <hi>Woe vnto them who ioyne money to money, till there be none
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150798:44"/> left for the poore to borrow.</hi> This is the City woe: which bringeth a neceſſity of borrowing vpon intreſt.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, falſehood and deceit in defrauding one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their monies at the times appointed, ſo as being diſapointed of their owne, they are compelled to take vp of others, or to ſhut vp their doores. Theſe three fold cart-Ropes, not eaſily broken, haue drawne a neceſſity of vſury vpon Cities. And ſhall it therefore be reputed no ſinne? God forbid: it is no good conſequence neyther in perſons nor eſtates.</p>
                     <p>Not in perſons. S. <hi>Paul</hi> telleth vs of an heart that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not repent,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> which heapeth vnto it ſelfe wrath againſt the day of wrath. Is impenitency in that heart no ſin, becauſe cuſtome hath made it neceſſary?</p>
                     <p>A drunkard hath brought his body into ſuch an habit, that vnleſſe he drinke bountifully, euen to the turning of his braine, he is ſicke againe. Is not drunkeneſſe in that perſon ſinfull, becauſe ſo neceſſary?</p>
                     <p>But for the lender, which is the Vſurer, there is no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour or pretence of any ſuch neceſſity which can befall him: ſeeing he hath authority from God as ſteward of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: and power amongſt men as owner of his money: for variety of lawfull and vndoubted imployments.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>2 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Common-wealth of the <hi>Iewes</hi> did ſtand without vſury, therefore why may not ours?</p>
                     <p n="2">2 You may find a diſcouery of the infinite iniuries this kingdome endureth by the vnlawfull trade of vſury.<note place="margin">In a tract a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vſury preſented to our high Court of Parliament. 1621. Item in vſury arraigned and condemned. 1625.</note> Where the allegations commonly made in defence of vſury, are ſufficiently anſwered.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Vſury is the cheefeſt cauſe of the greateſt miſery in this Land, as well to giue occaſion of great waſte as alſo to make much want, and will be in the end, the vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all, if it be not looked to in time. The Romans neuer began to decay, till vſury Lorded amongſt them,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Wilſon.</hi> of vſury. Epiſt. dedicat.</note> for then priuate gaine thruſt out common profit, luſt was
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150798:45"/> holden for law, idleneſſe more vſed then labour, ryot inſtead of dyet, vice better regarded then vertue, no charity at all, no loue betwixt man and man, but eueryman for himſelfe, and the whirle-poole of pride and ryot ouerfloweth in all things, and in all places.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="argument">
                  <head>10 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Propoſition.</note>No vſury is forbidden by the law of God, and by the law of nature, but that which is hurtfull, and ioyned with the hurt and loſſe of the neighbour.</p>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Aſſumption.</note>But ſome vſury is not hurtfull, but rather helpfull to the neighbour.</p>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note>Therefore ſome vſury is not forbidden.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Firſt the propoſition is vntrue, and of dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: for the law of God forbiddeth all vſury in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> p 293.</note> as a thing in it owne nature and in his whole kind ſimply vnlawfull, without any reſtraint or limitation, euen as it condemneth adultery, lying, theft, or any other noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſinne. Thus a man might argue for an officious lye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But they proue their propoſition thus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Propoſition.</note>Vſury is not forbidden, but as it is againſt charity, for cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is the ſumme of the law, and he which obſerueth the rules of charity, keepeth the law.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Aſſumption.</note>But that which is not hurtfull to the neyghbour, is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt charity.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Concluſion,</note>Therefore that vſury which is not hurtfull to the neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is not forbidden.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 To the Propoſition: Charity which is the ſumme of the law, hath reference towards God; towards our neyghbour, not onely in priuate, but alſo in publike: and towards a mans ſelfe. And in this ſence I acknowledge the propoſition of his ſyllogiſme to be true, viz. That vſury
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150798:45"/> is not forbidden, but as it is repugnant to charity. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the aſſumption of this ſyllogiſme is proued to be falſe, for there be many things which are not perhaps hurtfull to our neigbhour in particular, with whom we deale,<note place="margin">Note.</note> which are notwithſtanding repugnant to charity. The officious lie helpeth the particular neighbour, in whoſe fauour it is told, yet becauſe it is repugnant to verity, it is repugnant to charity. God who is truth hath forbidden all vntruth, and he will deſtroy euery one that ſpeaketh lies: the lying mouth deſtroyeth the ſoule: therefore no lying can ſtand with that charity and obedience which we owe to God, nor with that loue which we owe to our owne ſoules. So in like ſort ſuppoſe that the borrower ſometimes is not hurt by vſury, but rather holpen: yet notwithſtanding all vſury is againſt charity, for the practice of it cannot ſtand with charity and our allegance to God; who hath forbidden it, denounced his iudgements againſt it, made gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to them that will do the contrary: nor with our cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and duty to our Countrey, vnto which vſury is in many reſpects noyſome, as hath beene ſhewed: nor with that loue which we owe to our owne ſoules; for whoſoeuer putteth forth to vſury, or taketh increaſe, he ſhall not liue, but dye the death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p>Yea but ſay they againe, to proue the former propoſition, That vſury which is ioyned with the hurt of the neighbour is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: therefore that which is not ioyned with the hurt of the neighbour is not condemned.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>I deny the conſequence: for there are other reſpects which make vſury vnlawfull,<note place="margin">Idem p. 297.</note> beſides the hurt of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as euen now I ſhewed; by the ſame reaſon the patrons of officious lies might argue thus; God forbiddeth vs to tell a lie againſt our neighbour, therefore the lie which is not againſt the neighbour, but for him, is not forbidden. But you will ſay, all lying is forbidden: ſo is all vſury, as I haue already proued.</p>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:150798:46"/>
                     <p>And thus I haue ſhewed againſt the propoſition that all vſury is vnlawfull, though all were not hurtfull. Now I adde againſt the aſſumption of the firſt Syllogyſme, that all vſury is hurtfull: hurtfull I ſay, eyther to the borrower as commonly it is, or elſe to the Commonwealth, as before hath beene proued.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="argument">
                  <head>11 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>To lend vpon vſury and to borrow vpon vſury are relatiues, therefore if to lend vpon vſury be a ſinne, it is a ſinne to borrow vpon vſury, and if to borrow vpon vſury be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, then is it lawfull to lend vpon vſury.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>I Deny the conſequence which is grounded vpon a falſe ſuppoſition.<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> Pſ. 15. p. 305.</note> That there is alwaies the like reaſon of rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues. The oppreſſour, and he that is oppreſſed: the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and he that is robbed, are relatiues: but ſhall we hence conclude,<note place="margin">He which bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes vpon v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, neceſſity compelling ſinnes not, Idem p. 338.</note> that if to be robbed, or oppreſſed is not a ſinne, therefore it is not a ſinne to rob or to oppreſſe?</p>
                     <p>He which vpon neceſſity, yeeldeth to pay vſury, doth ſuffer wrong and is oppreſſed: therefore ſuch a one ſinnes not. Which may be thus proued.</p>
                     <p>To ſuffer wrong is not ſinne.</p>
                     <p>The borrower which vpon neceſſity yeeldeth to pay vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, doth ſuffer wrong. Therefore he doth not ſinne therein.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>Reply.</head>
                     <p>He which borroweth vpon vſury is not oppreſſed, becauſe he is willing to borrow vpon vſury: yea, and ſo willing, that he ſeeketh to the vſurer, and intreateth him to lend, offering to giue him conſideration according to the Statute, that is to ſay, Vſury.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>He that borroweth vpon vſury in caſe of vrgent neceſſity
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150798:46"/> doth yeild to vſury againſt his will, yea although he both offer and promiſe it: for in caſes of vrgent neceſſity, men ſeeme many times willing to that which is indeed againſt their will. When a man is in danger of ſhipwracke, how will he beſtirre himſelfe to vnlade and lighten the ſhip, and with ſuch earneſtneſſe caſt his goods into the ſea, that he may ſeeme to be very willing to be rid of them: and yet the thing which he willeth,<note place="margin">See the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the 2 argument for vſury,</note> is not the caſting away of his goods, but the ſafety of his life. This is a conditionall neceſſity. Thus the borrower is no more willing to pay vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then that man was to caſt away his goods: but his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for auoyding a greater inconuenience, makes him ſeeme willing to that whereunto ſimply he is vnwilling.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>2 <hi>Reply.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The vſurer cannot accompliſh his ſinne without the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower, therefore the borrower is partner of the vſurers ſinne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>The conſequent is not good.<note place="margin">Idem p 344,</note> The ſinne of rape cannot be without the innocent party that is rauiſhed, yet ſhe that is rauiſhed, is not partner of his ſinne that committeth the rape. So likewiſe one man cannot oppreſſe, vnleſſe there be another to be oppreſſed, nor impoſe vſury, vnleſſe there be another on whom it is to be impoſed: and yet he that is oppreſſed is not partner of the oppreſſors ſinne, nor the borrower who vpon neceſſity borroweth vpon vſury, of the vſurers ſinne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="reply">
                     <head>3 <hi>Reply.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>It may be doubted of, whether one may take money for his vſe of an vſurer: 1 Becauſe it is not lawfull to conſent to him, that doth euill. 2 Nor to giue occaſion to one of euill, as he ſeemeth to doe, that taketh money vpon vſury. 3. And <hi>Ieremy</hi> profeſſeth,<note place="margin">Ier, 15:10, Bb. <hi>Babing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> vpon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, p 70.</note> that he neither gaue nor tooke to vſury, where the Prophet plainely inſinuates, that if he had done eyther, hee could haue found iuſt cauſe in himſelfe why he ſhould be euill thought of.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:150798:47"/>
                     <head>1 <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">
                        <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Smith,</hi> in <hi>Willet,</hi> vpon Leuit. p. 336.</note>1 He conſenteth not to the ſinne of the vſurer, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vp money of him, he conſenteth to the lending, which is good, but the hard condition in lending, the vſurer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, and the other is forced to accept, becauſe of his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Neyther doth he giue him occaſion of ſinning, but of lending, the vſurer himſelfe <hi>Sumit occaſionem peccandi,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth occaſion of ſinning.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The word there vſed by the Prophet, is <hi>Naſhah,</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>mutuo dare,</hi> to lend, as <hi>Iun.</hi> well tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth, as it is taken in other places, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15, 2. <hi>c,</hi> 24.10. where the <hi>Septuagint</hi> interpret it by the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> debt not vſury, and ſo <hi>Theodotion</hi> here readeth, <hi>I did owe nothing to any man:</hi> the Hebrew word <hi>Naſhah,</hi> with <hi>He,</hi> ſignifieth ſimply to lend, but with <hi>Aleph,</hi> to lend vpon vſury, as <hi>Eſay</hi> 24.2. and though the vſuall reading be receiued, it ſignifieth no more then this, that the Prophet had no trading at all with them,<note place="margin">Cautions in borrowing vpon vſury.</note> (as we ſay) he neyther bought nor ſold with them and yet they hated him. Wherefore the reſolution here is, that a man for his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary occaſions may make vſe of an vſurers money, but (not to make gaine of it by letting it out againe. 2 or to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his pride, gaming, drunkenneſſe. 3 Or to compaſſe great matters in the world,<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> in Pſ. 15 p 318, 319, 320, &amp;c.</note> or to purchaſe Lands, or Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. 4 Or to ſeeme poore, that he may giue nothing to the vſe of the Church, or to the Commonweale in ſubſidies and taxes. 5 Or when he may borrow freely, at the firſt motion offering vſury to the lender) but driuen to it of neceſſity: for, <hi>non qui patitur, ſed qui facit iniuriam peccat,</hi> not he that ſuffereth, but he that doth wrong, ſinneth: and it is a very like caſe, as when a man vſeth the oath of one that ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by falſe gods: as <hi>Iacob</hi> did of <hi>Labans</hi> oath, that ſware by the god of <hi>Nahor, Gen.</hi> 31.53. who ſerued other gods, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 24.2. to confirme the league betweene them, as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>Non peccato illius, ſed pacto bono, quo fidem ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uavit,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150798:47"/> vtitur in bonum,</hi> he doth not vſe his ſinne in ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by falſe Gods, but his couenant, whereby hee kept his fayth to a good end: <hi>Epist.</hi> 154.<note place="margin">Note.</note> And like as a man fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the hands of Theeues doth reueale vnto them his treaſure to ſaue his life, which otherwiſe he ought not to doe: as the tenne men did to <hi>Iſmael, Ier.</hi> 41.8. So it is when one vrged by his neceſſary occaſions falleth into the Vſurers hands. But better were it to preuent ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, if it may be: and being once enwrapped, to follow the wiſemans counſell: Giue not reſt vnto thine eyes; till thou haſt deliuered thy ſoule,<note place="margin">Not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in debt to Vſurers.</note> as a Doe from the hand of the hunter, and as a Bird from the hand of the fouler, <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.5. For as a Bird taken in a lime-buſh, ſo one by dealing with the Vſurer, the more beſnareth and entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth himſelfe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="argument">
                  <head>12 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Neſhech, which ſignifies biting vſury is vnlawfull. But tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe vſury is not ſo.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>IT is the nature of all vſury to bite,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Fenton</hi> of Vſury p. 9. All Vſury bites</note> though with great difference: ſome like the Engliſh Mastiue, ſome like the dogge-ſlie ſome ſcarce ſenſibly, and therefore not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued to be a ſinne.</p>
                     <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Why Vſury ſeemes not to bite.</note> becauſe many are content to moderate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in this gaine, and then, if it be a ſinne, it is but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle one, as <hi>Lot</hi> ſayd of <hi>Zoar, Gen.</hi> 19.20. <hi>Modica ſunt quae perdunt nos;</hi> they be thoſe little ones that vndoe vs. A Moate in the Eye if it be not got out in time, may grow to a pin and web; and a mans conſcience may ſuffer Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke aſwell vpon a Sand as vpon a Rocke.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, it is not euer ſo ſenſible, becauſe as the Vſurer moderating himſelfe doth not ſeeme to bite the borrower: ſo the borrower releiuing himſelfe by others, hath no cauſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150798:48"/> to complaine. Yea, many borrowers concurring in this practiſe, by their multitudes, are able to ſway and inhance the market, in ſuch manner, that they may liue themſelues and pay the vſurer beſides. So that in concluſion thoſe do all ſet vpon the Commonwealth: which being a great bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, is able to beare many dogs, before ſhe need to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine: and feeling the wound (as in time ſhe muſt) ſhe knoweth not well of whom to complaine.<note place="margin">Multorum manibus grande leua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur onus.</note> Burthenſome therefore it is to the Commonwealth, yet ſo diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many, that it is the leſſe ſenſible, but neuer a whit the more allowable.</p>
                     <p>For theſe and the like cauſes the biting of vſury being ſometimes not ſo ſenſible to particular perſons, almighty God in his wiſedome foreſeeing how ready men would be to cauill at the Word <hi>Neſhech,</hi> hath of purpoſe expreſſed his meaning more fully by the exegeticall addition of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other terme, which ſimply ſignifieth any increaſe at all. And this hath he done, not onely in the comments of the Prophets.<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.17. Pro. 28.8.</note> But in the very text of the law it ſelfe, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 25.36, <hi>vetarbith,</hi> and the 37. <hi>Vbemarbith:</hi> which word, <hi>Salomon</hi> forgetteth not to adde: for <hi>Salomons</hi> daies being both peaceable and rich in ſiluer and gold, men would be then more ready in all likelyhood to deuiſe any cauill, or colour to maintaine that ſinne.</p>
                     <p>Neyther are theſe my priuate coniectures, againſt the groundleſſe diſtinction of biting and toothleſſe vſury; but M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                        <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe (vpon whom they ſeeme to relye as a chiefe patron of vſury) doth not onely condemne it as friuolous;<note place="margin">The diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of biting and toothleſſe vſury ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</note> but addeth further, that it was the purpoſe of the holy Ghoſt, by adding that other word to preuent ſuch cauils. <hi>Quia homines hac in parte nimium ſunt accuti et verſuti, et excogitant ſubterfugia, quibus crudelitatem ſuam tegant; ideo addit: et incrumentum non acceperit:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ſayth <hi>Caluin,</hi> men in this kind be ouer accute and ſubtile, and deuiſe euaſions how they may cunningly couer their cruelty, therefore he addeth in the text, Vſury or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150798:48"/> And for the diſtinction it ſelfe, <hi>Caluin</hi> his cenſure is, <hi>Ludunt homines ſuis cauillis, ſed deus non admittit tales verſutias:</hi> men cauill and play with words, but God ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth no ſuch ſleights. His meaning is ſimple and plaine, that all increaſe aboue the principall is forbidden.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="argument">
                  <head>13 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Vſury is forbidden to the poore, therefore lawfull towards the rich.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>THis euaſion is very friuolous: for <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19.<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> Pſ. 15. p. 202.</note> there is no mention of the poore, but all vſury is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den towards a brother, whether he be rich or poore.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 By the ſame reaſon we may conclude, wrong is not to be done to the poore, the widow, the fatherleſſe; or ſtranger; therefore wrong may be done to the rich,<note place="margin">Pro. 22.22.</note> to the married wife, to the children that haue their parents liuing, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Or when <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, Robbe not the poore, becauſe he is poore, we might inferre; therefore thou mayſt robbe the rich, becauſe he is rich.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Powels</hi> poſitions of vſury. p. 45. See the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the 3 argument.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>God in the lawes of vſury, did ſpecially, and by name forbid lending in that manner to the poore, for two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 To ſhew what care he himſelfe hath ouer them, who are commonly and vſually neglected of men.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Becauſe the poore are ſooneſt and eaſieſt oppreſſed of the rich, as the loweſt hedge is ſooneſt ſtepped o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 If the law of lending to the poore without vſury, ſhould inferre the lawfulneſſe of lending to the rich vpon vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; then it is euident that Gods intendment in thoſe lawes for the benefit of the poore ſhould rather proue a hurt and hinderance vnto them, becauſe by this meanes it would
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150798:49"/> come to paſſe that the poore ſhould not borrow at all.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Moſſe,</hi> of vſury: p 131.</note> For, who will lend to the poore for nothing, that might lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lend to the rich for vſury? of which poynt we haue ſo lamentable and euident experience in theſe our dayes, as no man, no not the vſurer himſelfe is able to gaineſay it. Yet of the two it were better for the poore man, that he ſhould borrow vpon vſury, then that he ſhould not be able to borrow at all: now borrow at all he ſhall not, if it be lawfull to lend to the rich for vſury, and not vnto him. And therefore as one ſayd, <hi>Maledicta gloſſa quae corrumpit textum:</hi> accurſed be that gloſſe or commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary that deſtroyeth the text: ſo may I ſay in this caſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill fare that interpretation which ouerthroweth the intent and purpoſe of the Commandement.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="argument">
                  <head>14 Argument for vſury.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Many by imployment of money borrowed vpon vſury haue growne rich.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam.</hi> in Pſ. 15. p. 257.</note>I Will not anſwer with <hi>Baſil,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that is, <hi>but I thinke more</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>haue come to the halter:</hi> but I thinke more haue proued banckrupts.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Wilſon</hi> of vſury. p 189.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Wilſon</hi> hath a pretty ſtory to this purpoſe, not vnworthy the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring. A man comming into a certaine Church, and ſeeing it fraught full of Images made of waxe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> demanded, what might be the cauſe of ſuch an vnwonted ſight? anſwer was made, that thoſe whom theſe images did repreſent were certaine perſons which on a time were ſaued from drowning by calling vpon our Lady. Nay then (quoth he againe) where be the Images of thoſe (I pray you) that called vpon our Lady, and were drowned notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? So ſay I in this caſe. If any man will ſet before me the inſtances, and as were the images of thoſe, who tooke vp money on vſury, and grew rich thereby: I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150798:49"/> on the other ſide, that he ſhew forth the hundreds, and thouſands of thoſe, who by that meanes haue vtterly impoueriſhed, and ouerthrowne their owne eſtate, they will be found to be without all compariſon.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Though ſome for a time may ſeeme to be rich by that which they haue borrowed vpon vſury, yet vſury at the length conſumeth them, and eateth them vp.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 Neyther doth this proſperous euent of the borrower iuſtifie the contract of vſury,<note place="margin">Note.</note> which couenanteth for gaine not in <hi>euentum lucri,</hi> but abſolutely, and therefore out of his loſſe as well as out of his gaine.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 And laſtly I adde, that the more the borrower is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched by this meanes, the more the Common-wealth is damnified. For whoſoeuer thriueth by occupying money borrowed vpon vſury, he hath ſo pitched the prices of his commoditie,<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> of vſury. p 174.</note> as that beſides a competent gaine rayſed for the maintenance of himſelfe and his charge, he alſo hath gathered vp an ouerplus of a tenth part for the vſurer. And thus by vſury the prices of all commodities are enhaunced, whiles the ſellers, who borrow vpon vſury, if they will thriue, muſt needs make the buyers to pay two ſhilling in the pound more then otherwiſe were ſufficient.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer to an Obiection.</note> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they which doe borrow vpon vſury, muſt needs ſell for ſo much as they may gaine both for themſelues and the vſurers. Therefore the reſt doe pitch the prices of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities accordingly. Otherwiſe they which trade with money borrowed vpon vſury could neuer thriue:<note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> in Pſ. 15 p. 255, 256.</note> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſometimes they doe thriue, it is euident, that all of the ſame trades doe ſo pitch their prices, as if all did borrow vpon vſury.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:150798:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Vſurers muſt repent of their ſinne, and make reſtitution.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vſurers muſt repent of their ſinnes.</note>AS for thoſe who haue practiſed this ſinne, their duty is to repent thereof, becauſe they that put forth their money to vſury ſhall not dwell in the Mountaine of Gods holineſſe, namely, vnleſſe they repent. And againe <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. He that putteth forth to vſury and taketh increaſe he ſhall not liue, but die the death, <hi>viz:</hi> vnleſſe he repent and turne from his wickedneſſe; for that condition is to be vnderſtood by warrant of the Lords owne expoſition, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.14, 15, 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bb. <hi>Downam</hi> in Pſ 15. p. 312 313.</note>Now vnto Repentance, beſides the inward loathing of the ſinne and ſorrow conceiued for it, is required (as that teſtimony; of <hi>Ezek</hi> 33.14.15. Plainely ſheweth) both a deſiſting from the practice of vſury, and a reſtitution of that which hath beene gotten by vſury, with the harme of of others. For the firſt: it is the expreſſe Commandement of God by the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28. Let him that ſtole, ſteale no more: and by <hi>Nehemiah</hi> more particularly in this caſe of vſury <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.10. Let vs ceaſe from this burthen; mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vſury: forſaking of ſinne accompanieth forgiuing of ſinne: <hi>Prou.</hi> 28 13. Neyther may we thinke that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth thoſe ſinnes, which we our ſelues retaine.</p>
               <p>Now vpon this forſaking of ſinne, will follow the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond duty of repentance,<note place="margin">Vſurers muſt make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion elſe. 1 No repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> namely reſtitution, as a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequent thereof, which reſtitution whoſoeuer maketh not, being able to reſtore, he neyther hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained repentance of his ſinne, nor any ſound aſſurance of the forgiueneſſe thereof. He hath not repentance: for he doth not forſake the ſinne of theft and vſury, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth in it, and he continueth therein that doth not make reſtitution. For ſo oft as a man remembreth, that whatſoeuer he hath vniuſtly gotten by vſury, or any other kind of theft, to the damnifying of others, is not his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150798:50"/> owne, but theirs whom he hath wronged, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth (being able) to reſtore the ſame,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Si res aliena propter quam peccatum eſt, cum reddi poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit non redditur, non agitur pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentia, ſed fingitur.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>2 No ſound aſſurance of remiſſion. Epiſt. 54. ad Maced:</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> ſo often he committeth theft. Therefore <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, that men doe not repent indeed, but counterfeit repentance, if when they are able to reſtore other mens goods, wherein they haue offended, they do not reſtore them</p>
               <p>As he hath not repentance which maketh not reſtitution, if he be able, ſo neyther hath he any ſound aſſurance of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. It is a true ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine, Non remitti pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum, niſi reſtituatur ablatum,</hi> that the ſinne is not remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vnleſſe that which hath beene vniuſtly taken, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, namely, if the party be able to reſtore: for whiles a man continueth in his ſinne, he cannot beleeue the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe thereof, and he continueth therein, vntill hee make reſtitution. To reſtore is to ceaſe from doing wrong, therefore hee that ſhall not reſtore, doth not ceaſe from the wrong.</p>
               <p>But it is further to be conſidered, to whom and when this reſtitution is to be made, and how farre forth.</p>
               <p n="1">1 To whom?<note place="margin">To whom vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore.</note> Surely to him that hath ſuſtained loſſe or harme thereby, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.7.8. That is, eyther to the vſe of the Debtour if he hath beene bitten or to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and godly vſes, if the Common-wealth hath beene endamaged.</p>
               <p n="2">2 When?<note place="margin">2 When.</note> So ſoone as thou deſireſt remiſſion of thy ſin, and reconciliation with God for ſo the Lord hath expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded. <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.6.7.8. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 6.2.3.4.5.6.7. <hi>viz.</hi> That the ſinne firſt muſt be confeſſed to God: Secondly, reſtitution is to be made to the party offended, the ſame day that thou ſeekeſt reconciliation with God, if not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and Thirdly a ſacrifice was to be offered, &amp;c. The equity whereof remaineth vnto vs, that in the third place we ſhould call vpon God for the forgiueneſſe of our ſinne, deſiring him for and by the ſufficient ſacrifice of Chriſt (which was prefigured by the ſacrifices of the Law) to forgiue our ſinne Many will ſeeme to ſeeke reconciliation
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150798:51"/> with God; but neuer thinke of making amends to their brother offended. But our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth vs ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſſon, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.23.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How farre forth this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is to be made.</note>How farre forth is this reſtitution to be made, that is, of what vſury, and of how much?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not of meutall vſury, where gaine for loane is intended onely and expected: for howſoeuer that intent corrupteth the act of lending, yet it polluteth not the free gift of the borrower, which is voluntarily giuen in teſtimony of thankfulneſſe. And therefore it bindeth not the lender for reſtitution to be made to the neighbour whom he hath not wronged, but to repentance toward God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">And of how much?</note>For the quantity; ſo much at the leaſt is to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as hath beene gotten by vſury with the harme of others: or if the offender bee not able to reſtore ſo much, yet he muſt reſtore ſo much as he is able. The Lord in his Law commandeth, that the offender ſhould reſtore the whole ſumme, and alſo adde a fift part vnto it, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.7. &amp; <hi>Zacheus,</hi> to teſtifie his repentance, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth foure fold: that thoſe men may know how farre they be from true repentance who will reſtore nothing at all.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall thinke or ſay, <hi>Durus est hic Sermo,</hi> this is a hard or harſh Doctrine, which is not ſo eſteemed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of other kinds of theft: I Anſwer, the harder this Doctrine ſeemeth to Vſurers then to other Theeues and robbers,<note place="margin">Note. Vſurers worſe then other Theeues.</note> the more deſperate is their eſtate then of others. And this may be another argument to aggrauate the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſneſſe of this ſinne, that whereas other Theeues and robbers, if once they be diſcouered, acknowledge their fault, and are willing to make reſtitution, Vſurers though conuinced of this ſinne, yet ſtand in defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of and thinke not themſelues bound to make reſtitution.</p>
               <p>I could with much facility, confirme the iudgement of this reuerend Father, by the concurrence of a world of teſtimonies; but becauſe the poynt is already diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered to be a manifeſt truth, I will but<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dyke</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance p. 143 Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> 2. Sermon vpon vſury and in his Sermon of <hi>Zacheus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion. Bb. <hi>King</hi> on <hi>Ionah.</hi> Ch. 3. 8.</note> name ſome of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150798:51"/> them that require Vſurers to make reſtitution, and preferre to the Vſurers conſideration, the iudgement of a moſt learned and iudicious Doctor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Powels</hi> poſitions of vſury p. 68. 69. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Philips</hi> Sermons p. 95. Bb. <hi>Sands</hi> in Sermon vpon, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74.75. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Rogers</hi> ſtrange vineyard p. 313. Bb. <hi>Iewell,</hi> vpon 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> p. 147. <hi>Perkins</hi> vol. 2. p. 197.</p>
               <p>If vſury be an vnlawfull trade,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Smith</hi> in <hi>Willet</hi> on Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticus p. 632.</note> as hath beene ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proued before; then it will follow, that what is wrongfully gotten muſt be reſtored home, and reſtitution be made of the wrong done.<note place="margin">Vſurers to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore.</note> So <hi>Zacheus</hi> profeſſeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence foure fold what he deceitfully had gotten; the word is [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] taken from ſuch as among the <hi>Athenians</hi> diſcouered thoſe which carryed out figs, which was forbidden, (they being had their in great price,) and ſo the word is generally applied to thoſe, that accuſe others wrongfully, and forge any cauillation againſt them, in like manner Vſurers haue trickes, and deuices to enwrap and entangle their poore debters.<note place="margin">Vſurers haue trickes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle their debters.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And if they will with <hi>Zacheus</hi> become the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> they muſt make reſtitution of their vnconſcion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vſury: ſo was it decreed in a generall counſell,<note place="margin">Councells de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones quae de Vſuris comparata ſunt, vendi debent, et pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia his, ex quibus vſurae extortae ſunt, reſcitui;</hi> poſſeſſions gotten by vſury, muſt be ſold, and the price giuen to them, of whom the vſury was extorted; <hi>Lateran.</hi> Part. 16. c. 5. and <hi>Augustine</hi> alſo would haue vſury reſtored: <hi>Quia omne, quod male poſſidetur, alienum eſt,</hi> becauſe euery thing, which is ill poſſeſſed, belongeth to another; <hi>Epist.</hi> 54.</p>
               <p>But here in this caſe of vſury,<note place="margin">Cautions to be obſerued.</note> theſe cautions muſt be obſerued.</p>
               <p n="1">1 That euery thing gotten by money cannot be reſtored, but onely thoſe things: <hi>Quorum vſus non est conſumptio,</hi> which are not conſumed in the vſe, as Houſe, Lands, but meat apparell, which conſume in the vſe, cannot be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but the value of them.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:150798:52"/>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides the vſury money, ſomething may be gotten <hi>humanâ, induſtriâ, by humane industry</hi> and for that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is not to be made.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And if the lender be damnified, <hi>Per dilationem,</hi> by the detayning of his money; of that alſo a conſideration muſt be had.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And all the price of the Houſe and ground is not to be reſtored, but <hi>Secundum quantitatem vſurae;</hi> according to the quantity of the vſury receiued. To this purpoſe, <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2. 29. 18. art. 3.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Adde hereunto, if the parties be not liuing of whom the vſury was taken: then reſtitution muſt be made to his heyres, and next of his kindred, and for want of them to be giuen to pious vſes according to the Law, <hi>Numb.</hi> 5.8. And ſo the Canon is: <hi>Qui vſuras receperint, cogendi ſunt, ſub pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ Excommunicationis, ijs àquibus extorſerunt, velhaeredibus restituere,</hi> they which haue receiued vſury, are to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled vnder paine of excommunication to reſtore them to ſuch, from whom they extorted it, or to their heyres, <hi>Lateranenſ. ibid. vbi ſupr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 30.18 19.</note>Now the good Lord pardon euery Vſurer, that prepareth his heart to ſeeke God, the Lord God of his fathers, though he be not cleanſed according to the purification of the Sanctuary.<note place="margin">Acts 26 18.</note> The good Lord open their eyes, and turne them from darkeneſſe to light, and from the power of Satan vnto God: that they may receiue forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance among them which are ſanctified by faith that is in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the God of peace, that brought againe from the dead our Lord Ieſus, that great Shepheard of the ſheepe, through the blood of the euerlasting couenant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>make them perfect in euery good worke to doe his will, working in them that which is well pleaſing in his ſight through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be glory for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Barnard. Serm. 61. in Cant.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Meritum meum miſeratio Domini.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:150798:52"/>
            <head>Mr. George Withers.</head>
            <l>TO make of griping vſury their Trade</l>
            <l>among the rich. No ſcruple now is made</l>
            <l>In any place. For euery Country-village</l>
            <l>hath now ſome vſury, as well as tillage,</l>
            <l>Yea they that lending moſt of all deteſt</l>
            <l>though but for tollerated intereſt:</l>
            <l>Doe nathleſſe take thoſe annuities</l>
            <l>which often proues the bitingſt vſuries;</l>
            <l>By nature money no increaſe doth bring,</l>
            <l>moſt, therefore thinke it a prodigious thing</l>
            <l>That money put to loane, ſhould bring in gaine.</l>
            <l>yet ſome of theſe by practice doe maintayne</l>
            <l>As monſtrous vſuries: and nought at all</l>
            <l>are touched in their conſcience therewithall.</l>
            <l>In vſury of Cattell or of Leaſes</l>
            <l>we may disburſe our money for increaſes</l>
            <l>More biting farre then thoſe who dare to take</l>
            <l>who by meere lending doe aduantage make</l>
            <l>As money naturally produceth nought,</l>
            <l>ſo, by the earth ſmall profit forth is brought:</l>
            <l>Vntill both coſt and labour we beſtow,</l>
            <l>for little elſe, but thornes and weedes will grow.</l>
            <l>The Landlord, therefore, here I dare auer,</l>
            <l>to be no leſſe a griping Vſurer,</l>
            <l>Then is the money maſter: if he breake</l>
            <l>the rule of Chriſtian charity, and take</l>
            <l>More profit then his Tenant can afford,</l>
            <l>and ſuch as theſe, are hated of the Lord.</l>
            <l>Of Vſurers there are ſome other ſorts</l>
            <l>who keepe no certaine place, but both in Courts,</l>
            <l>In Cities, and in Country-townes they dwell,</l>
            <l>and in the tricke of griping they excell;</l>
            <l>There be of theſe, that Vſe for ſilence take</l>
            <l>ſome others, an Vſurious profit make.</l>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:150798:53"/>
            <l>Of their authorities, and doe aduance</l>
            <l>their wealth by giuing others countenance:</l>
            <l>Their carriages their neyghbours fetch and bring</l>
            <l>they haue their ſeed time, and their harueſting</l>
            <l>Diſpatcht almoſt for nothing: ſuch as theſe</l>
            <l>are many of our Country Iuſtices.</l>
            <l>Some by another engine profit catch,</l>
            <l>they muſt be prayd and paied for diſpatch</l>
            <l>Yea Clerkes; and many of other officers</l>
            <l>are greater and more hatefull Vſurers,</l>
            <l>Then they that moſt are hated for that crime</l>
            <l>ſince theſe doe often for a little time</l>
            <l>Which they delay vniuſtly take what may</l>
            <l>of no meane ſumme, the annuall intereſt pay,</l>
            <l>Theſe men are cruell: and yet worſe by farre.</l>
            <l>moſt Treaſurers, and their pay-maſters are</l>
            <l>For, that which due vnto vs doth remaine</l>
            <l>they doe not onely ouerlong detaine,</l>
            <l>But, oft, of euery hundred, twenty take,</l>
            <l>ere payment of our, owne, to vs, they make</l>
            <l>They muſt haue bribes, their wiues muſt haue Caroches.</l>
            <l>or horſe, or Iewels, after which encroches</l>
            <l>Their ſeruants alſo, for ſome other dues</l>
            <l>(as they pretend) which if we doe refuſe</l>
            <l>To pay vnto them, twiſe as much we leeſe,</l>
            <l>this tricke enricheth alſo. Referres</l>
            <l>In Chancery, and in ſome other Courts</l>
            <l>and this or makes, or marreth moſt reports:</l>
            <l>This is that common cheat, and meanes by which</l>
            <l>meane officers ſo ſpeedily grow rich,</l>
            <l>Although they giue large Incomes, by this way</l>
            <l>their wiues ſo on a ſudden grow ſo gay,</l>
            <l>That were but Kitchin-mayds few yeares before</l>
            <l>yea many in the blood of Orphanes poore</l>
            <l>Haue dide their gownes in Scarlet by ſuch courſes</l>
            <l>and clothd and fed themſelues with widowes curſes.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Withers.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
